<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The herds-man's mate, or, A guide for herds-men teaching how to cure all diseases in bulls, oxen, cows and calves, gathered from sundry good authors, and well approved by the authour, in his thirty years practice : also many cures found out by himself, and never yet written, gathered into this portable volume, and sent abroad for the good of the common-wealth ... : being very profitable for all those that either have, or take charge of keeping this laborious, good, and fruitful kind of cattle / gathered and prosessed by Michael Harward.</title>
            <author>Harward, Michael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B24029</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17154152</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206326</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240890058</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1095</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">17154152</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B24029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206326)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1616:54)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The herds-man's mate, or, A guide for herds-men teaching how to cure all diseases in bulls, oxen, cows and calves, gathered from sundry good authors, and well approved by the authour, in his thirty years practice : also many cures found out by himself, and never yet written, gathered into this portable volume, and sent abroad for the good of the common-wealth ... : being very profitable for all those that either have, or take charge of keeping this laborious, good, and fruitful kind of cattle / gathered and prosessed by Michael Harward.</title>
                  <author>Harward, Michael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 122, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Tooke ... and are to be sold by Joseph Wilde ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 21-22 and 27-28 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Veterinary medicine --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Domestic animals --  Diseases --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Cattle --  England --  Diseases.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:2"/>
            <p>THE Herds-mans MATE: Or, a GUIDE for Herds-men.</p>
            <p>TEACHING How to Cure all <hi>Diseases</hi> in Bulls, Oxen, Cows, and Calves </p>
            <p> Gathered from sundry good Authours, and well approved by the Authour, in his Thirty Years practice.</p>
            <p>Also many Cures found out by himself, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet written; gathered into this portable Volume, and sent abroad for the good of the Common-wealth, and Kingdom of <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and all places else where need is.</p>
            <p>Being very profitable for all those, that either have, or take the charge of keeping this labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, good, and fruitful kind of Cattle.</p>
            <p>Gathered and Professed by MICHAEL HARWARD <hi>Philom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DƲBLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the King's most Excellent Majesty; And are to be Sold by <hi>Joseph Wilde</hi> Book-seller in <hi>Castle-street.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:3"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mich: De Laune,</hi> Reverendissimo in Christo Patri, ac <hi>Michaeli</hi> Archiepiscopo <hi>Dubliniensi,</hi> nec non <hi>Hiberniae</hi> fummo Cancella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio E Sacris.</p>
            <p>June 6. 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:3"/>
            <head>To the <hi>NATIVES,</hi> and others the Inhabitants of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The <hi>Authour</hi> wisheth health and prosperity here, and eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness in the Kingdom of Heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen, Neighbours, and Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I came into this fertile I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sland, I have heard of many men that have sustained great losses by the death and morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Cattle; many whereof might have been saved alive, by the skill and industry of a painful and laborious <hi>Oxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leech.</hi> But I see very few that bestow any pains in that noble Science: And those few almost wholly neglected, by reason that the Natives; and many of our English-Irish lukewarm Protestants, when any disease happens amongst their Cattle, do not look for help till some store of them be dead, and then to save those that are yet alive; they make use of those that have charms, Inchanted water, Inchanted Rings, and Bells. And so by Diabolical means get help for that time. Not remembring that for saving the life of a beast, they indanger the loss of their precious Souls, unless they repent truly, as I doubt
<pb facs="tcp:206326:4"/>few do. Others drive their Cattle, some <hi>10,</hi> some <hi>12,</hi> or <hi>16</hi> miles, to force them through a River; which they call a <hi>Murren-ford,</hi> and some loose more by hasty driving in summer, then by the disease it self.</p>
            <p>Now to save all this toyl, and also the hazarding of your eternal happiness, by using ungodly and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolical means, I say to save all this, I have here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed you a natural way, a way which God blesseth. If in subordination to him, we make use of those juices, herbs, plants, and minerals, which he hath caused the earth to contain and bring forth: both for food, and to cure all diseases both in man and beast. Now if you get help this way, you may give thanks to God, and say; the Lord is my helper, and deliverer in whom I trust, and to whom I seek in time of trouble, and be hath comforted me. But if you receive help the other way, you may pay the Charmer, and say; I have got help by Satans means, he is my helper, to his wayes will I trust, and to his Servants will I seek for help, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Friend, what I have painfully gathered, well approved, and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously used, I offer to thy view; If thou please to make use of it; thou wilt receive the profit. If thou cast it by and use thy old magical way, I have told thee before what gain thou art like to receive. However like or not like, use or not use, it hurts not me. I have done my duty, and cast my two mites into the Treasury; have given my Talent to the Exchangers, not daring to hide it in the earth, nor lodge it with me in my shrine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M.H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:4"/>
            <head>To the courteous Reader, that intends to practise in this most excellent, needful, and necessary Art.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riend (if I may so call thee) who ever thou art, that readest this small Treatise, if thou do it only for pleasure, it may add some profit also; but much more if thou practise. For, what more pleasure canst thou have in any earthly imployment, then to recover thy sickly beast to health by thy labour and industry? wilt thou not receive it as a blessing from <hi>Jehovah?</hi> and return him thanks with a joyful heart, yea, not thine own onely, but also the sick and fainting beast of thy Neighbours, or friends. If thou be a Gentleman or one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to do it freely, thou shalt have the prayers of many; and the bowels of the poor shall bless thee, If thou beest poor, &amp; not in a capacity to give freely, the labourer is worthy of his hire; yet be willing to cure, improve Gods blessings, take pay of the rich: but oppress not the poor and needy, rather give then receive, thou knowest a poor mans cause being so thy self. But what ever thou art, Gentleman, Farmer, or day-labourer; If thou intendest to serve thine own Town, Parish, or Countrey about thee in this pleasant, and charitable imployment. Thou are to
<pb facs="tcp:206326:5"/>understand that all. Arts consist of these four parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Fore-knowledge, Precept, Rule and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary; and as in these there is no Redundancy, so there is as little lack; for by fore-knowledge thou must foresee what the disease is, and what remedies to use. By precept thou shalt be taught what to do in all cases, together with Rules for thy orderly pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in the work. And by Commentary, thou shalt understand what accidents have, or may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in any cure, of all these thou shalt be instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the following work. And if thou wilt be as careful in learning and practising, as I have been in collecting and composing, no doubt but thou wilt prove a good proficient to thine own profit, and the good of all thy neighbours.</p>
            <p>But be sure thou have an accurate and ready head, a good memory, and an active and nimble hand, together with resolution and boldness, yet careful and vigilant, not rash nor hasty; if thou wantest these qualifications, thou art not fit to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister physick, much less to perform day chirurgical operation. The signs of all diseases and sorances, I have set down before the cures; be sure to get them ready in thy mind, before thou offer to practise; for it is preposterous to be learning, when thou shouldest be practising. And to make thee prompt and ready in the Arts, it is good for thee to go with some one that doth practise, (if there by any near to thee) and see how he gives medicines, and performs his chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal operations, and observe the event, it will much embolden and prompt thee, when thou art to act thy self. Forget not this premonition, but premeditate on
<pb facs="tcp:206326:5"/>it, and what else is requisite and necessary for thy Calling, so go on chearfully, and the <hi>Lord</hi> give a blessing to thy labours.</p>
            <p>When thou art called to a sick beast, be sure to take good heed of these signs following, for they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad; and many times death follows in a short time; yea, sometimes immediately.</p>
            <p>First, if the beasts mouth be cold within, and his lips begin to be pale and lank, death is near at hand.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his eyes sunk down into his head, with a ghastly look, ad a sharp-sented breath, not one of these escapes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the horns being very cold, and the beast careless, not taking notice of any thing, death.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the beast lying along on the ground groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and if you raise him up to sit, he full down again carelesly, present death.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, if thou put fine hay, grass, or the tops of oats between his jaw-teeth; if he eat it not, a bad sign, and few recover.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, His nose dry and soft, a bad sign.</p>
            <p>There are more signs of death, which I will not insert here, but where I treat of the Diseases, unto which they are appropriated.</p>
            <p>Good signs are, dew drops on the top of the beasts nose, his mouth warm, his eyes full as in health, his horns warm, sitting as in health, though sick, the belly not swoln, if he piss or dung being walked, if he chew and eat such meat as is put into his mouth, or between his jaw-teeth, all these are good signs.</p>
            <p>But if he once chew the Cud, then he is safe for that time, if his disease be acute; but not so in chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical
<pb facs="tcp:206326:6"/>diseases, which are of long continuance, as I will shew in their due places. But observe these well, and thou wilt hardly fail in giving judgment of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, or death.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M.H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206326:6"/>
            <head>Ague in <hi>Calves,</hi> or other Cattle.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE cause of this disease, is cold and wet sitting in their houses, also sitting on much hot dung, and having the cold wind blowing on them through a door, or open wall. But for those that are in the fields abroad, the onely cause, is, the intemperature of the Air, being now every hot, and anon very cold: So that the cattle are first chaft with heat, and presently chill'd with cold; And this unequal temper stops the veins and pipes of the liver, whereby its natural opperation is hindred, and breedeth raw un-concocted juice, whereby the constitution of the Body is altered, and that is the cause of this Ague or Feaver in Cattle.</p>
            <p>The signs are, watering of their eyes, and heaviness of their heads, which they will hang down, and also dribling at their mouths, their veins beating with great heat over all their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, (saith <hi>Mascall.</hi>) But in all my Thirty years practice, I have ever found them hang down their heads, their eyes look dim and waterish, their mouths colder then ordinary, their bodies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:206326:7"/>lank and lennow, and cold withall, refusing to eat, or suck if Calves.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>If they be Calves of a good Age, and at grass, them let them blood under the Taile, <hi>viz.</hi> in the vein on the under side the Taile, four inches from the Rump, and give to each calfe half a pint of water, wherein is boiled one good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Colewort leaves, chopt very small, and one peny-worth of Salit-oyl, and a spoonful of Salt, give this quantity to each calfe three mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings together fasting, and walk them gently half an hour, and let them not drink in two hours. If you want Cole-wort leaves, then take in their place a good handful of the leaves and roots of plantine, and use them as the other: Also change their pasture, drive them to some place where they may have young and tender heath to eat, and sweet and open Air, if you have not heath, then let them have fresh grass, but not too ranke, for that is not so good.</p>
               <p>If your calves be young and suck, then give them the foresaid Medicine at night after their sucking an hour or more. But loose no blood in this case, but make their house clean, and give them clean straw; for fear by the heat of their dung, and smell thereof, they get the Flux in their bellies; which in this case will be worse to cure then the other disease. In the day time put them out of doors into some fair close, or yard till night, and remember to give your drench three dayes together and it helpeth, often proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:206326:7"/>
            <head>Of the Feaver in great Cattle.</head>
            <p>THe causes of this more dangerous feavers, are the same as before, onely there is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter flux of raw humors ingendred, by heat and cold intemperately mixt.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Signs.</head>
               <p>The signs of this Feaver are, his eyes wax hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and are dropping, his head lumpish and heavie, his mouth foming and lavering, and drawing long his breath, with pain and much groaning, and some time he will sigh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>To cure this disease, you are to keep him a day and a night without meat or drink, the next morning draw a little blood in the vein under the Taile, then about an hour after, you shall give him thirty small Trunchions of Coleworts, sodden in Salit oyl, and salt fish water, and make him to swallow it, do this five morning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fasting, and give him the tender branches of Lintile pease, Olive branches or buds of the vine, and rub or chafe and cleanse his lips, and thrice a day give him cold water to drink, and keep him in the stall till he be whole and sound, so saith <hi>Leonard Mascall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others say first let the Beast blood in the neck vein, and save the blood in a bason, and stir it well that it clot not together, then take a pint thereof, and a pint of strong bear, and a penny-worth of Salit-oyl, and a good handful of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine leaves, and as many colewort leaves, being all chopt very small, set them on the fire and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206326:8"/>boile them well, then take them of the fire, and being no more then blood warm, give it to the Beast, and walk him an hour after, and use him as is taught before: both these are very good, but my order is as followeth. First I let the Beast blood in the vein under the Tail, then I give him a pint of reasonable strong brine, wherein is boiled a good handful of colewort leaves, or plantine leaves and roots, which of them is soonest got, and stamped small; give it blood warm, and walk him gently an hour after, if he be able, then drive him to some heathy land if you have it, or give him the green leaves of Hazel, or Ash-tree leaves if you can get them, or green Cabage leaves, if he eat not, put a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle at a time into his mouth between his jaw teeth, if he eat it there is good hopes: but if he drink clear running water, and eat, or but pick and chire grass the cure is done, often proved. Give this medicine three dayes together, if need so require.</p>
               <p>But here take notice of an accident, which once hapned to me in this cure, in the latter end of <hi>April,</hi> 1649. I was called six miles from home to medicine a Cow, which was despera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely sick of a Feaver, and full of crude homo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, first I let blood, then gave the medicine, and rowled her dowlap with a root of black Helebour; but she appeared much worse for three hours, then I gave her one quart of strong beer, wherein was boiled one penyworth of long Pepper and Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and one ounce of Anniseed beaten small,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:206326:8"/>and one penyworth of Salit oyl, this troubled her exceedingly, so that she lay down as to dye, and the Gentleman her Master gave her for lost, yet her mouth was warm, her horns hot, and dew drops did sometime appear on her nose: We left her laid all along and went to Dinner, which was long being many, and it Sunday; when we came forth she sate up, and looked somewhat better, we went to the Church to Evening prayer, that being ended we hasted to our cure, and found she looked very well, we got her on foot, and found her Udder swoln as big as a milk-pale, which I scarified very well, and it run abundance of water and blood, much like to water wherein blody meat had been wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I also rowled the udurn just through the skin with strings of hair, in four or five places, to give the peccant humors way to issue forth, which run a main, so we gave her Oats and Hay and left her that night, and by the next morning she had eaten a good part of two great Oat sheafes, and some Hay, and with the loss of her milk recovered: And at the next <hi>Easter</hi> she was a gallant Beif. This I noted for thy learning, if thou have the like accident.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the pestilent Feaver.</head>
            <p>I call it the pestilent Feaver, because it is very contagious, as the Pestilence or Murren are, and also to difference it from the other feavers which are more mild, and not infectious at all.</p>
            <p>The cause of this violent and contagious fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, is, the infection of the Ayr by the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206326:9"/>of the cold, at such times as there are plenty of hot vapors; yet quickly beaten away with their cold Antagonist; now these hot and cold vapors are made contagious, or healthful by astral influence <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any will have this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease to proceed from corruption of blood, he may be pleas'd to understand, that nothing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts the blood so soon as intemperate Air, by the influence of the <hi>malevolent</hi> aspects of Stars; If you say it comes by intemperate weather, I answer, the weather is caused by the Aspects.</p>
            <p>If you will have it caused of great wet and inundation of waters; I answer, great and long wet, and many flouds may cause a Rot in Cattle, as I shall declare hereafter, but not this pestife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous disease.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Signs.</head>
               <p>In this feaver the Cattle stand for the most part under Hedges, Bushes, or in dry ditches, with their four feet near together, and hang down their heads, and crouch so that their backs stand up, and they shake and quiver much in their flanks and thighs, and also on their ribs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind their shoulders; their mouths and horns intemperate, sometime very hot, and soon cold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and eateth little or nothing, then the cure is hard, and few being so escape. And truly, our common illitterate Ox leaches in <hi>England</hi> lose many of this disease, for want of knowledge, and all they can say is, the Cattle are bewitcht.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>First divide the sick from the whole, for one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206326:9"/>will infect many. Then let the sick blood in the neck vein, let them bleed well; but so, as not to weaken them, remember this in all thy cures. The blood will be thin, and of a light red colour, as though it were mixt with white, and it will froath much, the more the worse: also it will quickly turn to water, so that no sign of blood appears but froath onely, then he is far spent, and hath need of speed and help:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Medicines.</head>
               <p>Take the juice of Camomel one ounce, the juice of Rue half an ounce, and the juice of Colworts three ounces; if ye want Colworts take plantine leaves and roots, boil these juices in a quart of new Beer or Ale a walme or two, then take them from the fire, and put into the Beer so boiled, of Frankincense one dram, and of Cassie one dram, being first desolved in two ounces of the best Treacle, mix it very well together, and give it to your Beast being blood warm, and walk him gently half an hour after, and see that you keep him warm in the house, and keep the house clean and sweet, and give the medicine three dayes together in the morning fasting: Besides what you give the first time. Also take of <hi>Castorium</hi> one scruple, and of <hi>Assa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetida</hi> as much, desolve these in one good spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the juice of Sage, and two spoonfuls of Aquevite; and with a spoon put it into both his ears, and some black wool after it, also tye his ears with some inkle, or such like, to keep in the medicine, lest with shaking his head he loose it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206326:10"/>keep it in his ears three or four dayes, and if it be any where near to be got, then let him drink no water for two or three dayes, but that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Eldern Roots have been boiled, they being first cut, or beaten small, for want of Eldern Roots use wheat bran.</p>
               <p>Be diligent to get these medicines in time, and thou wilt not fail on thy cure.</p>
               <p>Also thou must not forget to look well to those that are in health, for as many as were in his company are in danger of being infected: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to secure them, give to each of them half a pint of urine, wherein a good handful of Hens dung hath been dissolved, and strained out again, and before they go from your hand, give to each beast one spoonful of Tarr, and anoint the tops of their noses with Tarr also. Do this three dayes together, <hi>Probatum est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Murren.</head>
            <p>THe cause of this Infectious disease is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Air, (as I found once in two Towns in <hi>Cheshier, Withinton,</hi> and <hi>Sithinton,</hi> where a dark stinking fogg continued three dayes together, in the middle of Summer; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one week after many of their Cattle were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with this disease: I was called thither, and found the disease so predominate, that I was forc'd to go from field to field wit a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn and Candle to give medicines to sick Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) Also is taken by stinking caren lying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buried, or from other infected Cattle; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it makes a quick dispatch, for after it once
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206326:10"/>begins, they are dead within twenty four hours, if help be not found, therefore delay not.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Signs.</head>
               <p>The ancientest writer I read teacheth many signs to know this disease, which in my practice I have found to signifie other diseases: All which I shall insert in their due places, and will here shew what I have ever found true.</p>
               <p>When a beast first beginneth to be sick of this disease, his mouth will run of water, and drivel like as a hungry Mastive, or Hound will; but soon after he will rattle in his throat, and draw his breath very heavily, and forsake his meat; And commonly they begin to swell a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the knot of the wind-pipe, thence to the end of the jaw bone, to the Cheeks, and so up to their ears; some swell in the dow-lap which is easily cured, and some in other parts, as a Cow in her Udder, or the Cod of a Bull, this curable, the other difficult. When any beast dieth of this disease, you shall see in taking off the hide, the disease will appear in the swoln place under the skin, like a yallow jellie, and of a bad sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: but in this case be careful, let not him that fleays the dead come near the quick, for fear of infection: and he that drencheth the sick is not to come near the sound, till he change his cloathes and wash his drenching horn, want of this care loseth many a beast that might be saved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>First you must consider whether your beast be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206326:11"/>cureable or not, which you may easily do: For if he be much swoln amongst the veins and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes in the head and throat, he is not cureable. Secondly, if he rattle in his throat, and strive much for wind, not cureable, Thirdly, if he foam and froath at the mouth, and his breath stink, not cureable. The signs of death I shew'd at the first, you may have recourse to them. Now if you find your beast not cureable, yet sat, or in good flesh; then you may kill him and make use of the Bief, for his flesh is good all but the swoln place. I have caused some drest, which have been sold before the other of the same company were drenced.</p>
               <p>Now for the cure, first if the sickness be but newly begun, and there be no swelling nor rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his throat, then let him blood in the neck vein, and let him blood, till the blood that comes be thin and red, not black and thick: This done give him a quart of strong beer, or Ale; wherein is boiled two ounces of <hi>Angelica Roots,</hi> wild Carret Roots, wild Parsnip Roots, or the Root of the Sea holm, which of these you can first get, and one ounce of Fennel-seed, beat your Roots and seeds small before you boile them, and give the medicine blood warm. Then take half an inch of the Root of black <hi>Helebory,</hi> and put it into the corner of his dowlap that hangs at his knee, make a hole with an Awl just at the lower edge thereof, where the two skins stick together; scrape the black skin of the Root, before you put it into the hole, leave it in,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206326:11"/>and it will cause the dowlap to swell and run of water, and so cleanse his whole body. This hath been often proved with good success.</p>
               <p>Of all the Herbs you use for this disease, there is none like to <hi>Angelica,</hi> either the Roots or the juice of the green leaves.</p>
               <p>If the dowlap be swoln already, then your cure is, to slit the skin and fley it on both sides from the sore place, so far as you perceive any yellow jelly, or water, or till you come to sound flesh, then rub and chase the fleshie sore very well, with beaten Garlick and salt mixt together, to the end it may draw the peccant humor out at that place, that it do not infect the whole body. The like course is to be taken if he swell under the jawes, if he do not rattle in his throat, but if he rattle or wheese no cure.</p>
               <p>Some bold fool-hardy illitterate <hi>Ox-leaches,</hi> do fley up the skin, and pare away the corrupted flesh, which is tolerable in the dowlap onely, not near the throat, (where commonly it first ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,) for if you cut a vein or sinew you get a second cure, perchance worse then the first: therefore take heed, I was warned by other mens harms. Truly I never lost any which I so fleyed and drest for this disease, which were many. But whether you fley onely, or fley and cut away the bad flesh, be sure to put a big tent of beaten Garlick and salt butter into the new sore, and stitch up the skin so that the tent may tarry in, and the matter may issue out. Also remember to blood and drench this beast as the other, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:206326:12"/>you must not fail to drench all those that are sound, with <hi>Angelica</hi> if you can get it, if you cannot get <hi>Angelica,</hi> then use urine and Hens dung, as is taught for the pestilent feaver before.</p>
               <p>If this disease do first appear in a Bulls cod, he may be cured by gelding and dressing, These are often proved. Give your Cattle meat and drink as is taught before.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Garget an ill Disease.</head>
            <p>Of this Disease I must amply speak, and shew the cause and cure for the several kinds thereof: for there is the <hi>Garget</hi> of the Tongue, the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get</hi> of the Throat, the <hi>Garget</hi> in the Maw, and the <hi>Garget</hi> in any out part by some push or stroak given.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Garget</hi> in the Throat.</head>
               <p>THis is caused by corruption of blood, which by the force of the expulsive vertue, is beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from the vegitable parts, (where it would cause the pestilent feaver) to the superficies, and there causeth a swelling.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Signs.</head>
                  <p>It commonly beginneth to swell under the Beasts chops, and is at first like to a bladder of water; such as a rotten sheep will have, then his lips will wax thick and slimy, and swell back to his throat, and up his cheeks to his ears, as the <hi>Murren</hi> doth: some begin to swell in the dowlap first, and so it goeth along the throat to the cheeks and ears, and backward to the brisket and belly: And when it is swoln so big that he cannot stoop to eat, then he soon dieth; And
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:206326:12"/>when he is dead and in fleying, the swoln place will appear very like the <hi>Murren,</hi> but that there will no blisters arise between the flesh and the skin, as doth in the <hi>murren:</hi> Also this difference is between them, that these eat till they are hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the swelling, and the other do not. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so these live four or five dayes, and some more: but the other dye within twenty four hours if remedy be not found, as I told you before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Cure.</head>
                  <p>If the swelling be but newly begun, either under the chaps, or in the dowlap; it may be quickly cured as followeth. First slit the skin so long as the swelling is, then fley it up on both sides till you come to sound flesh, then rub the sore well with beaten Garlick and Salt, and leave a good lump of bruised Garlick in the sore, on both sides, then stitch up the skin gently, that it may have room to issue forth, and let him go to his meat as before, for the cure is done, often proved, this is my own way.</p>
                  <p>Others when they have fleyed up the skin as aforesaid, do take fair white sifted Ashes of wood, and mix them with the grounds of old stale urine, and stir them well together: then also wash the fleshly sore therewith, some do boil it first, and then wash therewith, both wayes are very good. Then close up the skin again, and anoint it with Tar and oyl mixt, or ye may lay thereon a plaister of Nettles bruised and mixt with salt, or a plaister of pitch. <hi>Moscall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if he be much swoln, and you be forced
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206326:13"/>to fley a great breadth, then your best and onely cure is, when ye have plaistred the sore, then to wrap it with some big woolin cloath to keep it warm, and if it be in wincer keep him in the house the night season, and drive him out in the day. This disease being much swoln either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the chaps, or in the dowlap and breast is not easily helpt. Yet some silly practitioners will tell you all will be well in a little time: But in that time it often comes to pass that the beast dieth. This I have often seen, wherefore my advise is, if he be much swoln, and the beast be fat, then kill him, and cast the infected part away, but the rest is good meat, you may safely eat it, if he be not sat, then act and do your best to recover him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Garget on the Tongue.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Garget</hi> on the Tongue of a beast oxe, or cow, is a certain swelling under the root of his Tongue which will cause his head and face to swell, and to froath also at the mouth, he will then forsake his meat in often gulping in his throat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Cure.</head>
                  <p>You must cast your beast on some straw for bruising, &amp; then take forth his tongue, and with the point of a sharp knife slit along the middle vein under an inch long, right from the root of his tongue, and there will come forth black blood and water, which cometh from the gall. Then ye shall rub the place with salt and vineger
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206326:13"/>mixt, and so he will recover and do well again, often proved <hi>Masc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though this Author say often proved, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not say one proved. For truly I ever found this the worst of all Gargits, but I was never cal'd to any beast sick of this disease, till the tongue was swoln so big that it hung out of his mouth, and he could not eat at all; and though I used the means prescribed, and caused the beast to be fed with milk, yet mist the cure. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if once a beasts tongue be sore, and swoln as abovesaid, then my advise is, as in the former Gargit, for fear you loose your labour and your beast. What I speak in this case is not by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say, but by experience, the cure is hard and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Garget in the Maw.</head>
               <p>THe Garget in the Maw of a beast, Oxe or Cow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is an ill disease, and some very hard to cure.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Sign and cause.</head>
                  <p>It is a swelling in the beasts belly, caused by eating green or dry Corn, and drinking much water after his great glut of Corn. It is also caused eating many Crabs, or Acorns; or browsing, and feeding much on green Oak-leaves, and buds in <hi>May</hi> or <hi>June.</hi> Now let me speak to each of these a part, as I have found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>If your Cattle eat much Oak-brouce in the spring, when it hath young leaves on it; it will lye undigested in the paunche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and thence go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206326:14"/>into the stomack, where it should be digested and made small even as the dung which they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void: but there it drieth and baketh together, so hard that it cannot easily be cut a sunder when the beast is dead. Neither can it be mollified with medicine, but with his heat and driness, burneth and drieth all those small infolded skins; then nature ceaseth to work, having lost her tools, and the fabrick soon falls. The green leaves of yew are of the same nature, if much of them be eaten.</p>
                  <p>Also if your Cattle eat many Crabs, they will set their Teeth on edge, and then they will swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them whole, and fill their paunches so full as they can hold, and there they lye and rot, and so destroy the beast: For, into the stomack they cannot come, neither is there room for these un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruised bodies to enter in amongst these weak and tender skins. And the like may be said of Acorns, for if they eat many of them and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them whole: as commonly they do when their Teeth are edged with Crabs; Then they sprit and gnaw in their Mawes, and few escape death.</p>
                  <p>And if they do chew them well and swallow none whole, yet by long eating thereof, and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no grass, they will dry and harden in their stomacks, as is said of the green leaves before.</p>
                  <p>Also there is a Garget in the Maw by eating green or dry corn, which may cause your Cattle to dye, if they be not carefully looked into.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:206326:14"/>
                  <head>The Cure.</head>
                  <p>Take a good quantity of whole Mustard-seed, and mix it with strong Wine, or Ale, and give it to the beast. Another, chop and then bruise small a good handful of Gamomile, and then mix it with Wine, and give it to the beast.</p>
                  <p>Another, take a handful of Juniper crops or berries, cut them, and then bruise them all small: then mix it with wine and give it. Another, take penyrial, Rocket, and garden mint, of a like quantity, stamp them together, then put to it a pint of Wine or Ale, and let it stand close cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all night, on the morrow strain it, and give it the beast. Another, take a good handful of the leaves and roots of Avance, wash them, and then lay them to soak all night in Wine or strong Ale, then on the morrow stamp them, and then strain them, and so give it the beast. All these remedies are found good to digest, and also for the cleansing of the maw saith <hi>Mascal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>These medicines though they are good, yet some of them are hard to get; others long in preparing. I use the first, to which I make this addition as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>First I bruise the mustard-seed, but not small; then two or three good spoonfuls of it, I put one ounce of Salit oyl, and as much treacle; and I put these in a quart of strong Beer, or Ale, when it is new and working in the vessel, if it may be got so; or the newest I can get, mix it well together, and give to your beast, to each sick beast this much. This you must give many
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:206326:15"/>dayes together as you see need, for, it is not once, or twice that will serve: If the disease come by eating green oake browse, Acorns, or Crabs; for, as by long eating thereof, they are brought to this spoiled condition: So by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministring physick often, they must be recovered, if at all. I have known some dye of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease (caused by green oake leaves,) when this medicine had digested, the dry and hard sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in the stomack, two or three inches round about the edges, and caused the beast to scowre, yet all the middle remained hard: and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fouldes of skin therein dryed, and dead. If this disease be caused by eating oake browse, Acorns, or Crabs, let your Cattle have water at pleasure, for want thereof hastens their death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, if your Cattle get the Garget, or do swell by eating green Corn, either in the blade, or in the cars before it be ripe: Then give them neither meat nor water till their swelling asswage; but walk them gently in some fair field or lane, and give them the medicine if you please, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum est.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If your Cattle, either Oxe, Cow, or any of that kind; yea, Horse or Sheep, do by chance break into your field of dry Corn, or to your ricks of Corn, or thresht Corn in your Barn, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially Barley; Then give them the medicine, but very little water to your beasts, or Horses, for they will drink till they burst their mawes: when they have walked and dunged once or twice, let them drink the more. Taking this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206326:15"/>course, I never failed of my cure. For eating green or dry Corn, whether Oxe, Cow, Horse or sheep: but I let sheep drink their fill.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Sheep cured of this Disease.</head>
               <p>Once I was called by a Gentlemon to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine Sheep for this disease, there were four dead, and one in dying, and twenty more sick, and like to dye. The cause of their sickness was not known, some said they had eaten some poyso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous herbs, others said bewitched, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this gave me no satisfaction, I slit the belly of one open, and found the maw exceeding full of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley peales: Then I said it was by eating Barley that the sheep were sick, the answer was, that they had destroyed much in the cocks, and had been a week in the Eddish, which was not raked nor gleaned. This by long eating Barley ears, their mawes were filled with the chaff, which remained there, when the Corn was digested and gone through them. I gave the foresaid medicine to the twenty sick sheep, to each sheep a quarter of a pint, and they all recovered and did well. So they that were thought to be worth no more then the skins would yield, were within one week after worth Six pound the score. This I note for thy learning, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, if the like accident happen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the windy Garget.</head>
               <p>THis is a substance of wind between the flesh and the skin, which raiseth all the flesh in small blisters, and bladders; such as deceiful Butchers use to raise their meat with, to make
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206326:16"/>it appear more plump and fair in the eyes of the buyer. This wind raiseth the flesh, and puffs up the skin so fast that you may see it move, as though something were creeping under the skin: and if you rub it with your hand it will rattle like a bladder of wind; and when it is cut open, it appears no otherwise but as beif or veale blown up with wind: and therefore I call it the windy Garget, it is a disease I have not heard of, nor ever see but once, it was a Cow to which I was fetch't six miles, in which time the disease had spread it self all over one side, from the shoulder (where it began) to the Flank and Loyns, and still went on fast.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Cure.</head>
                  <p>First I slit the skin in many places round about the edges of the swelling, then raised it up with my finger; and put into the sores bruised gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and salt, to draw out the wind and stop the rising, and as any place arose we made incision, and put in the same as before. There was fetch't an other Ox-leech also, and he thought the cause of this windy swelling was a substance of water lying in her upper belly under her heart, and desired licence to make an issue between two ribs: which being granted he did, and there came forth blood and water a small quantity. But whether his cure, or mine did the work I know not, but the Cow recovered and did well, and that gave us both content.</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:206326:16"/>
            <head>Of the Springs in Cattle</head>
            <p>THe cause of this disease is blood offending in quantity, and having no other evacuation, openeth the veins in the Arse-gut, and issueth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the drought, and so into the small guts, and stirreth up heat and wind, and stopeth the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament, so that the beast doth not dung at all, or but very little. The signs of this disease are. His belly will swell much, he will strike his head backwards to his belly, and stamp with his feet, and cover much to dung, yet do little, and that mixt with clotted blood.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure is.</head>
               <p>First you must take forth his dung, as far as you can reach with your hand, do it gently for fear of hurting the great gut: Then with a great pipe and a bladder, put a quart of warm Wine and moulten butter into his fundament, just as you give a Clister to a man; and hold a handful of rags, or soft hay thereto, to keep it in a good while. When that comes out, put in half a pint of the juice of Plantine and knot-grass, and keep it in as long as you can, do this twice a day for three dayes together. And once a day give him this medicine follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Take plantine a handful, knot-grass as much, and Shepherds purs half a handful, beat them very small, then put them in a quart of strong Beer or Ale, strain out the herbs, and give the beer to your beast with a horn.</p>
               <p>But if the swelling do not yet fall, then give your beast an ounce of Anniseed beaten to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206326:17"/>powder, and one head of Garlick pil'd and bruised, both boiled in a quart of good Ale, do this three or four mornings together fasting, and walk him gently.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Swelling of a Beast, Oxe, or Cow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by eating of a Tine worm. Swelling by eating venomous Herbs, or any poysonous grass. Also swelling by eating the <hi>Conoth</hi> worm.</head>
            <p>SWelling of a beast by eating of a Tine worm is a sore disease, for they will swell as big as the skin will hold. And if remedy be not found, they will dye within twenty and four hours. This worm is a small red creature, and round in shape, it hath many feet, and is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what bigger then a hogs louse, and doth creep amongst the grass all the summer.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Conoth</hi> worm, is a black worm, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny short legs, somewhat longer then half a rye corn, and her body about a singer long, she hath many black hairs thinly scattered all over her, also, she hath two eyes almost as big as a mouse: and if you touch her, she will sprent, and straight hold up her head, and look you in the face, as though she would leap at you. In her body is a yellow poysonous substance, like to the quitter that first comes out of a boyle: of which if any beast eat he swelleth, and in twenty four hours dieth, if remedy be not found.</p>
            <p>Now because by all these poysons the Cattle swell exceedingly, and there is no sign to know of which it is, neither can I give a true account whether it be caused by any of the three.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:206326:17"/>Therefore I ranke them altogether, and will prescribe one excellent remedy for all these poysons, and others also.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>Take Wormwood one handful, Rue half a handful, plantine leaves two handful, Mugwort a handful, and wild Carret leaves a handful, and half a handful of feather-few, beat all these, or so many of them as you can get in a morter very small, then put them in a pint of urine, stir it well together, and strain out the juice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding hard: then put to this juice a quart of strong Beer or Ale, and boile it till a quarter of it be consumed, then take it from the fire, and dissolve in it one ounce of the best Treacle, and two heads of Garlick, finely pilled clove by clove, and beaten very small, and half an ounce of Mirrh in powder, mix all these well together with the Ale, and being blood warm give it to the beast, and walk him gently an hour after, and let him not eat for an hour and half after, do this two, or three mornings together fasting. Others use for eating of all poysonous herbs, and for eating the field spider also, whereby a beast swelleth) To give the juice of plantine and wild carrets by equal porportion, give it with a little vineger. Also the juice of mugwort mixt with Ale or Beer and given, others give of Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers or goose-grass stampt and strained, and given, it is a special remedy against the venom of the field spider and others also.</p>
               <p>Also the Garden Tansey stampt and strained
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206326:18"/>and given with Wine, or the seeds of the great Cow-thistle dried, and made into powder, and given with Wine, or the roots thereof boiled in Wine and given.</p>
               <p>Likewise Garlick stampt together with Ale or Beer and given. Any of these are good alone to be given to a beast, when he is swoln by eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any venomous thing. And if you take of some herbs two parts together, it will then be stronger &amp; take more effect: but in this case use them with discretion, even as you see cause. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Crowling, or crying of the Guts, and fretting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in Cattle: more properly the Trenches.</head>
            <p>THe cause of this disease is much Cattar or Rume, falling down from the head upon the Liver: so infeebling the natural heat thereof, that it is not able to concoct the juice of the meat, sent thither by the stomack: but leteth it pass crude and raw into the veins. And thus the whole body is filled with raw juice, which falling on the guts causeth the Trenches.</p>
            <p>The signs thereof are, much rumbling in the beasts belly: and crying of the guts. Also a flux and scowring.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>Take five Sypress apples, with so may gall nuts, with old wheat the weight of both the other two, then beat them well altogether, and put it into three pints of red Wine, and give the beast by even proportion thereof four mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: and ye shall not forget to put thereunto (if you can get them) lentile pease, of mints,</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:206326:18"/>
            <head>Pissing of blood called Meand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>water.</head>
            <p>This disease is gotten by some strain, or other hurt in the Reins of the back, whereby they are so weakned, that they are not able to distill the watery substance of blood, sent thither from the liver, but the sucking veins draw it thence, while it is yet raw, like blood and water mixt: or like water wherein bloody flesh hath been wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and so the water pipes send it to the bladder, and thence it descends to the spout.</p>
            <p>
               <hi> The signs are the colour of the urine.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head> The Cure.</head>
               <p>Take of sharp Tanners owze, before any lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come in it, with the powder made of old <hi>Martlemas</hi> Bief that is lean, mix and stir them well together, and give the beast, this is good and well proved. And the juice of madder gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with honied water is good. These and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more are taught by <hi>Mascal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> I <hi>use these two following, which never fail if taken in time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of Bolearmonick beaten to powder one ounce, and one handful of the herb called Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew, or, <hi>Rosa-solis,</hi> and beat it small, and put these two into a quart of new butter-milk, hot out of the churn, and give it to your beast in the morning fasting, three mornings together, it is a present remedy often proved, not written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The best of all remedies.</head>
               <p>Take one ounce of Ising-glass, unwrap it, and chop it small, then put it into a pottle of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:206326:19"/>good new milk, and boile it till half the milk be wasted, then give it to your beast in the mor<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
|ning fasting, blood warm, do this three mornings together and it helpeth, often proved, and in desperate cases.</p>
               <p>The herb called Sun-dew, or <hi>rosa-solis,</hi> is a little low herb, growing in boggs, and mossie base land: the flowers of it grow on small streams about two inches high, and hang at the top of it on bunch, much like the buttons of a band-string: and are in colour white and red mixt. The leaves are about the breadth of ones little finger nail, at the brodest end, and narrowest at the stalk, they are of a red colour mixt with green: and full of small hairs, and have a dewie-moisture (much like to oyl) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes on them; especially when the Sun shines hot and clear, and they lye on the earth except, grass, or moss held them up. They are in their prime in <hi>June,</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> gather them in one of these months, dry them in the shadow, and keep them for winter, pull them up by the stalks, and put them in a dish, for fear you loose the dew on them which is of great vertue.</p>
               <p>Issing-glass, and bole-armonick you may have of any <hi>Apothicary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Dew-bolne in Cattle.</head>
            <p>THis disease in Oxe, Cow, or other beast, is swelling in the body as much as the skin may hold, this is very dangerous for bursting: it is gotten by eating of the Trefoyl grass in a dewy-morning, (as some say.) But I am not of their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:206326:19"/>mind: for I constantly see the contrary, in Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle that eat great store of this grass and swell not: also others that have very little thereof and yet swell, I rather think it to be caused by eating some poisonous herb or grass, except the cattle feed in very ranke ground before it have been well nipt with frost: in which case they will swell exceedingly, if the swelling be not caused so. Then there is no difference to be found be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this swelling, and that of eating some poisonous thing; for in both there is great store of wind between the great panch and the back so, that sometimes the hollow above the flank, will be swoln above the back bone; if the wind be in the hollow of the belly, and not in the great panch it will swell exceeding high, so that by pressing it with your hand, you may perceive it to be in the body: for, on the right side near to the loin, you may press hard with your hand, and feel the great panch hard, and the skin and flesh puft up about it, which would not be if the wind were onely in the great panch.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>Some do chafe and drive him softly up and down to make him to dung, if that do not help, then ye must rake him and take forth his dung, if that serve not, then they strike a hole with a knife in the hollow part of his back above his flank, and there let out the wind with a quill, and so he will recover again: also give him rue, or gard en tanzey, stampt with Wine or Ale to drink, or give him a quart of verjuice, <hi>Mascal.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:206326:20"/>
               <head>But my way of Cure is.</head>
               <p>First I rake him and take forth his dung, as far as I can reach with my bare arm, and this I do with good heed for fear of hurting the great gut, then I rub the upper part of the gut, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the back-bone with salt, and so drive him softly up and down half an hour: if he break wind and dung there is good hope of a cure. If he continue sick and swell still, and I perceive a great substance of wind to be betwixt his body and the great panch and his bowels; Then I take a sharp launcet in my right hand, and with my left hand press down the beasts swoln flank close to the loin on the right side, and if it be possible thrust my four fingers under the edge of the loin: Then thrust your lancet close to your fingers, with the point straight forwards as though you would cross over the beasts body, between the guts and the loins: thrust or strike your lancet so deep till the wind puff out, then put in a big quill, and stitch it to the skin, one half in and the other out, so that the wind may have free passage to issue out, and let it remain so till the beast be well. Also give your beast every morning one pint of good Ale, and one head of garlick stampt, four or five dayes together. Now if the wind that comes out stink much, and this remedy help not: then make use of the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines for eating poisonous herbs, prescribed before. But before you give medicines, or loose out the wind, repair to the signs of death, and recovery: and consider whether your beast be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:206326:20"/>cureable or not. Also be careful with your lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet for fear of cutting the fat, and kidneys on the loin: or the guts that lye below it on the right side, Also the great panch on the left side. Reader be diligent to find the cause of swelling in Cattle, for a little mistake here looseth the cure. If Cattle swell by eating young grass in meadows, or any other mawn land, then walk them softly till they dung and they quickly aswage.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Blain on the tongue of a beast.</head>
            <p>THe Blain on the tongue of a beast, is a certain bladder growing above the root of his tongue against the pipe, saith <hi>Mascal.</hi> But I never found any bladder but on each side the tongue, near the root thereof.</p>
            <p>The cause of this disease is great chafing, and heat of the stomack: whereby (as some judge) it doth still grow and increase by more heat, for commonly it cometh in the Summer, and not in the Winter, <hi>Mascal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in all my practice I found this disease to be most frequent in the spring, and Autum, very rarely in summer or winter. And for the cause thereof (though <hi>Mascal</hi> tell me) it is chafing, and fast driving, and for want of water. I am not satisfied therein: for but once this forty years did I see a labouring Oxe, or drift beast have this disease, neither for want of water: but for the most part it comes to Cowes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cattle in <hi>March,</hi> and <hi>April,</hi> and the first half of <hi>May:</hi> when they labour not, nor are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:206326:21"/>driven, and had fair spring water at pleasure; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides standing pooles and ditches: which makes me think Mr. <hi>Mascal</hi> found not the cause of this disease. Now I judge the cause to be, either by eating or drinking some poisonous thing, which poyson being over-mastered by the natural bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som of the beasts body, is forced▪ by the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive vertue to the thin and weak parts of the internal skin: As the sides of the tongue hear the wind pipe, the Arse gut, the kidneys, and small guts. In these parts it will rise on blisters, and bladders full of wind and yellowish water: and if remedy be not soon found, death follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth immediately.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Signs.</head>
               <p>If it be on his tongue, he will blow hard, and hold open his mouth, his eye-browes will swell, and his eyes run of water. If he be far spent his eyes will be closed with the swelling of the browes and lids thereof. If it be in the belly or hinder parts, then will the fundament swell, and the flanks: but the surest signs are, swelling of the eye-browes, the eyes running of water, and the loud and troublesom breathing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>First cast your beast, then take forth his tongue, hold it in your left hand, and with your right hand break the bladders you find at the root thereof, near the wind-pipe, on each side there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The blisters, or bladders will be as big as a little egg, if you cannot break them between your finger and your thumb, then cut them with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:206326:21"/>a sharp short knife: or, prick them through with a bodkin, and loose out the offending mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But take heed of cutting too deep, for spoiling the beasts tongue: Then wash his tongue and mouth with vineger and salt, or with urine, and make him swallow a new laid egg-shell and all together, and he will quickly recover. But remember to walke your beast softly half an hour after, often proved.</p>
               <p>When this disease is in the arse-gut, then they use to put up their hand, and break the blisters, and rub it with salt, and so some recover.</p>
               <p>When it is within his body on the loins, and kidneys, then they cast the beast on his back, and tumble him too and fro, thereby to break the blisters. But there is one short, and sure cure for all these, which never failed me, it is this, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: when you come to a beast that is risen on, in any of the places aforesaid, then take a sharp pointed knife, or lancet, and let the beast blood in the vein under the Taile, a shaftment from the rump, and let him be walked gently till his swelling asswage. If he bleed overmuch, you may quickly stry the blood, by laying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the spungious dusty-matter that doth fill a dust-ball, or puffin; you may find many of them in old untilled lands that are sandy: or you may tye hares fur in the knot of a shoo-thred, or another small string, and lay the knot on the vein, and tye it fast till it cease bleeding, this must be done with discretion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:206326:22"/>
            <head>Milting of a beast.</head>
            <p>THis is a very sore accident for a beast, and many dye thereof: It is breaking, or hurting of the milt. It may be broaken or hurt with some blow, or sore stripe, (with goad or staff) or by a push with the horn of another beast, on his side, which makes him to faint and fall down, yea, many dye by a great blow along the side, when their bellies are full.</p>
            <p>The signs of this grief are, he will suddenly lye down in driving, if ye stop never so little. But when any shall so lye down, ye shall not raise him up suddenly again, but ye shall then turn him, and lay him on the other side, and so let him rest a while, to be refreshed again.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The curr is.</head>
               <p>Take of green Ash-tree bark one pound, shave, or scarpe off the outmost dry rind, beat the rest in a morter very small: then put to it a quart of strong Ale, and let it be close covered for one hour, then strain out the Ale and give your beast to drink, do this three or four mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings together, and he will do well, if the milt be not broken, if it be he is not cureable.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Want of digestion in Cattle.</head>
            <p>WHen a beast doth not digest his meat, there is a rawness in his stomack, which is known by his often belching, and his guts make a crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, his eyes will be full of water, his nerves and sinnes will be hard and stiff: because he doth not use to rub or lick himself.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:206326:22"/>
               <head>The Remedies.</head>
               <p>Take nine pints of warm water, and thirty colewort leaves a little boiled, mix them with some vineger, and so make him to swallow it down, and all day after ye shall let him eat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that. Also some do give unto the beast three ounces of beaten garlick in a pint of Wine or more, and then do drive him some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what fast a good while after, use this three or four mornings fasting.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Barbes in a beasts mouth.</head>
            <p>THe barbes in a beasts mouth, are certain lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle teats growing in the sides of his mouth, and every beast hath them. But they hurt not till they grow big and long, and then they trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him much, by coming between his teeth: and under his tongue, thereby hindering him for chewing his meat. The signs are, his bad and ill savoured eating, also the teats, or chags (as some call them) are long, very big, and of a blewish colour; especially those in the narrow part of his mouth behind his lips: for those will be very big, and long, lying under his tongue, and of colour very black.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is.</head>
               <p>First cause the beasts head to be holden fast, then put your finger between the beasts lips, turn the edge of the lower lip outward, and with a sharp pair of shears, or scisers, clip away these black and blew teats close to the skin, but cut not the skint Then rub the place with salt, and in a day or two he will be well, proved.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:206326:23"/>If the beast have not the barbs nor flux, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not eat his meat well, then give him the juice of garlick and onions with salet oyl, hold up his head and pour it into his nostrils: do this three mornings together, and he will be more desirous to eat.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Pallet of a beasts mouth inflamed.</head>
            <p>THis grievance doth so trouble a beast that he cannot well eat his meat, he will sigh often times, standing and weighing more on the one side, then on the other. The remedy is, ye must last him, and then race, or scarifie him on the pallet of his mouth, and make him there to bleed well. Then ye shall give him of red fitches wirhout huskes, mixt with green leaves, or some other herbs, but give him no dry meat, till he be through whole thereof, saith L. M.</p>
            <p>This cure pleaseth not me. First, because the pallet is a tender thing, and being cut or hurt doth not heal of a long time. Secondly, a beast is not a reasonable creature, neither can he be held fast by reason of his great strength: Also his mouth is deep, and a knife or lancet sharp; and his throat and wind-pipe near: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut are spoiled, or if a vein be cut the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of blood very hard to be staied. And in the third place the passage to the palate is narrow, and it cannot be seen perfectly: Therefore either the acting hand, or the beasts mouth is sure to be spoiled.</p>
            <p>My cure is, To wash the beasts palate, and his mouth, and the root of his tongue with the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:206326:23"/>whey of an Allom posset, as hot as I can abide my hands in it. To do this, tye a bundle of linnen raggs to the end of a stick, or splent made for the purpose: and let them hang like a fringe over the end thereof, to the end you hurt not the beasts mouth, do this three dayes together: Then wash other three dayes with white Wine vineger, and the juice of plantine, this a perfect cure, and well aproved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The pallate fallen.</head>
            <p>This is a bad sorance, and hard to be cured.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The signs are.</head>
               <p>The beast will take meat and chew it, but he cannot loose it down, and it will lye on great lumps in the sides of his mouth between his teeth and his cheeks, then he will offer to bite grass, but cannot his mouth being full before, and if you take all clean out of his mouth, then will he eat freely till it be full again, and then cease.</p>
               <p>To cure this sorance, you must make a piece of wood like to a great spoon, with a handle of a foot long, and as big as your finger: the bit thereof must be two inches broad, and made smooth as a spoon. Then cause the beast to be held fast, and take forth his tongue with your left hand and hold it fast: then let some one anoint the round side of your spoon-bit with pepper and mustard made with white Wine vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; Then with your spoon in your right hand, being thus anointed, apply the medicine to the pallet of his mouth which you shall see hang
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:206326:24"/>down towards his throat, and thrust it up to the end of the wind-pipe, and hold it there a little while; then loose his tongue, and take forth your spoon, and let him rest half a day: Then look in his mouth again, and if the pallet do still hang down, then dress your spoon as is taught before, and put up the pallet three or four times if need be, and wash his throat very well with strong white Wine vineger and pepper, proved.</p>
               <p>If thou be a learner and knowest not this member in a beast, then repair to some Butcher when he slaugtereth a beast, and he will shew thee the pallet of the mouth, what it is: and how it covereth the top of the wind-pipe when the meat goeth down, and moveth to and fro, as the beast taketh his wind.</p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Act not before thou understand.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Diseases of the eyes.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Haw in the eye.</head>
               <p>THis is a sinewous substance of flesh and skin, growing in the corner of his eye next his nose, and every beast and horse hath it: It doth support and hold the eye in the right place, and as the beast doth stir his eye it moveth over it, and is very useful, yet growing big and hard it doth not hurt but destroy the eye: if remedy be not soon found, if the hawes, offend, ye may know by these signs, first if his eye be sore and inflamed, and have not been hurt by stripe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> otherwayes, it is like the haw doth offend. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if the haw appear big, and the upper edge thereof be black farr on, also if ye see it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:206326:24"/>rub hard on the eye, then it is certain it doth offend.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Cure.</head>
                  <p>For this cure ye must have a good incision needle, with three square; or broad point, let it be three inches long, and so big, that a thred of two or three fold may follow it: it were good to have two of them, and keep them clean and sharp. When you go to use them, put double thred in them both: Then cause your beast to be holden fast, whether it be Horse, Oxe or Cow: And with the one take up the higher eye-lid, but stitch not to deep, and tie it to his horn, or a Horse to his bridle: so that the eye may stand open. Then with the other needle take up the haw, thrusting the needle through it, a quarter of an inch from the edge thereof: so having drawn the needle through, that you may pull up the haw with the thred, having both the ends in your hand; Then with a sharp knife or scisers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are away the black and hard edge of the haw, a little above a quarter of an inch deep in the middle, and so less towards the ends: let the piece you take of be one inch long, or less as you see need. This done, loose down the eye-lid that was tyed up, and have ready a dishful of fair water, which sup into your mouth, and with both your hands hold open the eye, and spout in the water by a little at a time, to wash the blood clean away: so loose the beast and he shall do well. Now if there be a film, or web grown over the eye (as oft there doth by the rubing of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:206326:25"/>the haw) then you are to use the medicine for the web in the eye, as it is taught hereafter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Web in the eye.</head>
               <p>THis sonance is a thick fil which covereth the eye, either all or some part of it: some of theso are white, some red, and some black: They may be caused by rheum falling from the brains, and then they are white; if the cause be a stripe, or other hurt, they are first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and after that blackish.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The remedies are.</head>
                  <p>Take white salt, and wrap it in a linnen cloath, and then take it in the hot embers, and burn it, then beat it to small powder, and with a goose quill blow thereof into the eye, and then hold your hand thereon a while, and ye shall see it water, and thereupon amend. Also the juice of the herb dragon to anoint the eye, is good against the web therein. And the juice of the wild lettice doth the like.</p>
                  <p>Also for a sore eye in a beast, ye shall spurt Beer therein, or chew the leaves of ground ivy, and drop it into his eye. And the juice thereof in like manner mixt with a little powder of Ginger. So far <hi>Leonard Mascal.</hi> But I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of <hi>Markhams,</hi> as followeth.</p>
                  <p>First let the beast blood in the temple veins, then take an egg and open it in the crown, and put out half the white, then fill it up again with salt, and then roast it in the hot embers so long and so hard, that you may beat it to a fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which done, dissolve some of that powder
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:206326:25"/>in a spoonful of the water of Eye bright, and a spoonful of the juyce of house leek, and with the same wash the beasts eyes twice or thrice a day, and it is a present cure.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>For a stroke in the Eye.</head>
               <p>TO cure this sore, ye shall take of the juyce of Centory herb, and mix it with a little honey, and therewith anoint his eye. Also make a plegit of fine flax anoint it with the medicine, and lay it plaister way on, the beasts eye, and make it fast for being shaken off: if it be in the summer, anoint the outside of your plaister with Tarr, to keep away bees, and flies, this is a good cure.</p>
               <p>Also for a stroke in the eye, ye shall take the crumbs of wheaten bread or other; and then soke it a little in rose water, or vineger, and so lay it to his eye and it will help. But if the eye be swoln or inflamed, then take Southren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood and bruise it with a little vineger and lay it to. Also the juice of pimper-nell is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all griefs of the eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or to be mixt with other things. Also against watering of Beasts eyes, as oft-times they will run of water. The remedy is to lay on browes or eye-lids the meal of dryed Barley, tempered with water and honey; Also the seeds of wild parsnips, or the juice of wild daysies mixed with honey, and so laid on or anointed therewith: which is good against any pain of the eyes. Then anoint it all over with Tarr and oyl mixt for fear of bees or flyes coming to the honey, <hi>Leon. Mase.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:206326:26"/>
                  <head>My Cure.</head>
                  <p>For the web, pearl, film or cloud in the eye of Horse or other beast I use the remedies fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which never failed me: neither will fail thee, if thou be diligent in applying them.</p>
                  <p>First I let the beast blood in the eye-veins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the eyes, then with a goose quill I blow into his eyes the fine powder of burnt Egg-shells, and hold the in-side of my hand over the eye a little while to keep it in. Then have ready a salve made of brown Suger-candy, and sweet butter without salt, well beaten together: put the bigness of a common field pease of this salve into his eye, and with your hand over the eye to keep it in till it be melted, then let him go for that time, do this twice a day till he be perfectly well proved. Another, take a stone of blew vitriol, called of some a Celestial stone. Wet the end of this stone in your mouth, and touch or rub the web on the eye therewith, yet so gently, that ye do not hurt the eye. Do this twice a day, and sometimes wash the eye with the juice of house-leek, and Aquevite mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the juice of true ground juye (if ye know it. It is called of some Ale-hoof, of others maiden-worth, and of some burn-grass, because it is so excellent a cure for burning, or scalding, and it is as good for eye sores.) Wash the eye I say, by spouting the juices, and Aque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite out of your mouth into it: And when ye wash forbear touching with the stone at that time. Do this once in two dayes, and touch with the stone the day between.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:206326:26"/>
                  <p>When the eye begins to mend, ye shall see the web begin to dye at the edges, and turn from white to a blackish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed colour: Also the web will begin to wear away at the edges first, and so clear the eye upwards, towards the pearl or sight thereof, and at last will grow like a wart or teat of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed flesh, just on the pearl of the eye; this teat you may take off, if your hand be active, and your wit acute and ready. First cast your beast, and tye up his eye-lid as I taught for the haw: then with a small nedle and threed take up this teat, and with the thin edge of a groat pare away the teat close to the eye, but beware of touching the filme of the eye: Then loose down the eye-lid, and wash and dress as is taught, and it is a perfect cure.</p>
                  <p>And for blood-shoten eyes, inflamed eyes, or eyes that run of water: or for dimness of sight, either in beast or horse, I never found a better remedy, then to spout into the eyes so grieved the juice of house-leek, and the juice of true ground Ivy by equal proportion, and as much Aquavite as both the other: do it as I taught to wash the haw, and fail not to wash the eye twice a day, at night and in the morning till it be well. This remedy hath not a second, for clearing, cooling and comforting, often proved.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The turn, or Thurning Disease.</head>
            <p>THis disease is well known, yet not to all by this name, for some call it the giddy, some the sturdy, others call them mazed beasts. But the disease is one and the same. It is a certain
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:206326:27"/>bladder of water, lying amongst the braines of the beast: in some there are two, three or four; And besides the water in them, there are many little white worms as big as a hogs louse: And as this bladder thrives it wasteth the brains on the one side, and presseth the other into a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the skull, also the putrified water which ariseth before the bladder, doth fret, and waer the bone of the skull so thin, that you may press it very easily with your thumb.</p>
            <p>The cause of this disease is not yet known to any: but some say one thing, and others say a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; yet all fabulous, and not worth mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in this place. But my opinion is, that it is onely a small substance of raw rheume inclosed in one of those little kernels of the brains: and sinding no passage out, neither by the nose, the ears nor eyes doth there putrifie, and soon after by heat and moisture is vivified and becomes many small worms: These are alwayes inclos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a husk, or cell, and do suck and draw the radical moisture from the brains into this cell wherein they live: and so by degrees the husk fills, and is like a bladder full of water, and the brains wherein it lyes, are corrupted and become like unto rotten Tallow.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The signs are.</head>
               <p>First the beast doth begin to hold his head aside, so that you may see one horn somewhat higher than the other, after he will stay behind his fellowes, and go much alone: and if you drive or chace him he will not go straight, but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:206326:27"/>turn to the side that is sound, which is the side he holdeth lowest: Also you can scarce drive him in at a gate into a field, but he will pass by on the one side. And at length will turn round so long till he can scarce stand, yea some times till he fall, also if you dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e him into any great water, he will then turn round and scarce be get out. Yet for all this pain and trouble he hath, he will feed well if the grass be good: but alwayes in danger to be lost by falling into pits or ditches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure, if Cureable.</head>
               <p>First consider whether he may be cured or not. Secondly, if he be ready for cure.</p>
               <p>First then if the turn lye in the hinder part of his head he will hold up his nose and turn but little, but in this case he is not cureable. Secondly, if it lye under the horn he will hold up that side of his head and is uncurable. If you can feel any part of his fore-head so soft that the bone will yield, being hard prest with your thumb, then he is ready▪to cur, else not: And as it is a difficult cure when the disease is ripe, so it is dangerous; yea, desperate when it is not ripe, and too late if over ripe, because the beast is then weak, and not able to undergo the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the cure. However, if your beast be fat, or well stricken in flesh, it is better kill him then venter his life in the cure, but if he be lean, and not fit for meat, then proceed to the cure as followeth.</p>
               <p>First cast your beast in a house upon straw or
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:206326:28"/>hay, then tye his four feet fast together with a small rope or cord, and cast the end thereof over some beam, that it may be held fast with more ease, then cause his head to be held fast also, and with a pair of sharp scisers clip away the hair of his fore-head and face close to the skull: Then with a sharp pen-knife cut the skin along one side of his fore-head, from the middle of his face, almost to the horn, then do the like on the other side: let your two cuts meet in a point in the middle of his face, and be five, or six in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches asunder at the top, so that the skin you raise may be in fashion like half a heart; Then fley up the skin, beginning at the sharp end, till you be above the soft place where the turn ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, then with a needle draw a strong double thred through the sharp end of the skin you have raised up from the bone, and tye it up to his horn, so that it hinder not your work: this done take away the blood with a linnen cloath, then press hard on the skull with your thumb, and where the bone yieldeth most, there cut out a round piece, as broad as an English shilling, do it with the stub of a knife, having a round edge like a half moon, hold the edge of your knife to the bone with your left hand, that when you strike it with a hammer in your right hand, it may cut just through the bone, and guide it to cut round, and through on every side, then take it out and cast it away: Then shall you see a strong yellow skin appear called <hi>Dura Mater,</hi> or <hi>Pericranium:</hi> It cleaveth fast to the brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:206326:28"/>Cut this skin with the point of your knife, as large as the hole, in the bone (but take heed of cutting deep for fear of breaking the bladder of water in his head, for then your cure is lost: for, when the water is gon ye cannot find the empty skin and worms; which being left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind destroy the sound brains in short time: yea, if but two or three of those worms remain in the beasts head, they will breed so many blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and within two moneths will be ready to cut again, if the beast live.) When this skin is removed there will appear a substance of rotten quitter, much like to the brains, but differing in colour, for the brains are white, mixt with small fiberous veins: but this quitter is yellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish white, and lyes in kernels as the brains do, but it is rotten. This you are to stroke away with a small splent made for that use, strok eit gently till you see the bladder appear. Then turn the beasts face downwards, and stop his wind by holding your hand fast on his nose, that he may strain out the bladder; but if you see the bladder breake and the water run out, then loose his nose quickly, &amp; catch hold on the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; the skin before you loose the sight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: then hold it fast, and draw it very gently for fear of breaking, and it will come out by leasure and the worms in it: Then hold the beasts face downward again, and power out the blood and water which are in that open head: This done take down the skin you tyed up before, and stroke off the blood which is on it, and the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:206326:29"/>skull also: then take one stitch through the sharp end of the skin that is loose, and another through the skin in the middle of his face, just where the other grew before, so lay the loose skin in its old place, and with your hand stroke it straight; and with that one stitch tye it down Then make hast to untye your beast (for fear he take hurt with lying long bound,) and tye a wollen cloth of two or three thickness before his face to keep it warm, make your cloth broad at the top, that it may reach to his Horns, and be tyed to them with two strings: Also let his frontlit reach to the top of his nostrils in length, and be tyed with two strings under his chin. Then tye him in the house, and give him good hay and oats to eat if it be winter, if in summer get him grass in your meadow, and shake it light in the Sun to wither one day before you give it to your beast; he will eat it the better; keep him in the house fourteen dayes, and give him but little water the first six dayes, only so much as to keep him for taking hurt. Now if any water or wind gather in the hallow of his head (as oft it doth,) it will hold out the skin over the hole in the bone, and raise it on a lump as big as a hens egg: and the beast will droop and not eat his meat; to remedy this, you must raise up the edge of the skin with a pen-knife and let the water run out, holding his head aside: then lay it close together again, do this two or three times as need is; and anoint the sore skin round about the edges with. Tarr and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:206326:29"/>Hogs grease mixt together, and it will both heal and keep away the flyes often proved. But be sure to be careful in tending and looking to these sick beasts; for therein is the greatest part of the cure: And let him that desires to undertake this, or the like accurate labour: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to some place where he may see the work done once by an active hand, which will be no small help to an ingenious wit.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Wood evil.</head>
            <p>THis disease makes a quick dispatch with a beast, if remedy be not soon found: The cause thereof is unknown to me, and the disease to any Author I have read for beasts of this kind: But for Horses, and Sheep I read <hi>Jervice Maak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Leonard Mascal:</hi> But neither the cause of the disease, nor the cures laid down by them doth any thing avail in this cure I am now to speak of, and teach what I have got by diligent study, and found true in many years practise.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The signs are.</head>
               <p>Fist, if this disease take a beast in his head, then doth he hold his neck a wry, yea turn it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most double: so that you would think he had a desire to look over his shoulder; Also he will reel too and fro, and still bow his head back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to one side, and if he fall down, then he doth lye on the contrary side, and cast his head back to his shoulder: he doth pant and blow much, and his breath is hot, and his body with extream pain. Also his breath smells like the hot broath of flesh that hath taken wind, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:206326:30"/>beginneth to slink: Then if remedy be not soon found he dyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is.</head>
               <p>First let him blood on the contrary side to the disease, and let him bleed well, yet beware of too much: Then take a handful of the green leaves of the herb Rue, beat it small in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or dish: then put to it a peny-worth of good Aquavite, then strain out the Aquavite and juice of the herb through a course linnen cloath; which done, take a spoon and fill both his ears with the said juice and Aquavite: and put in to each ear a little wool the better to keep in the medicine: also, tye his ears with two strings, else he will shake out the wool and juice both, do this two or three dayes, and it helpeth; often proved.</p>
               <p>If you cannot get this medicine so soon as need requires: Then let blood as is taught be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and beware of taking so much as to weaken your beast: yet you may let him bleed till it change from black and thick, to thin and more red: Then take him to some pool, pit or pond of water that is deep; tye a long rope about his horns and draw him into the deep water, and swim him a good while, then pull him out and let him rest a while, and see if he hold his head straight tis well; if not swim him again, but not long, then take him out, let him rest a little, then drive him home, and rub, and chafe him with dry straw till he be hot and dry. Then take one scruple of the fine powder of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:206326:30"/>Ginger, and as much powder of Peper, and two scruples of Nutmeg in powder, put these into three ounces of strong Ale, or Beer, mix it well together: and with a spoon, or a little horn for that purpose pour it into his nostrils, and use him as ye have been taught in other, diseases, and he will be well, this I proved twice.</p>
               <p>But here I must mind you of those things you were warned to be careful of at the beginning, which is the signs of death; which in this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease are, first, if the beast be faln down and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rise, neither stand when he is lifted up. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if the violence of the disease have broken his neck, as oft it doth. Thirdly, if he be down, and the disease moving violently from place to place, drawing the sinews so extreamly, that his flesh doth tremble and quake where the contraction is, and in a little time moves to an other place: and there cause the like pain and trembling; while the poor Creator torments its self, by tossing his head too and fro, and tumbling from side to side, till strength be gon, and he give himself for lost, and so in quiet breath out his last. But if this disease seise on the cheek or jaw-bone, then it will cause the bone to split, and rive into small shivers: also his teeth will rise up out of their places, and lye loose in his mouth: This beast will eat while he is able, and so live ten or twelve dayes and at last dye. For this kind of <hi>Wood evil</hi> I could never find any remedy, all that I could do failed.</p>
               <p>If this disease take Cattle in the finewes of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:206326:31"/>their legs only, then the remedy is to rub and chafe those sinewes with black sope and strong Ale boyled together: do it once a day for nine or ten dayes and it helps, or rub and chafe them with nerve-oyl in like manner both these are proved. The <hi>Wood evil</hi> in sheep is cured as in other Cattle: And for Horses I refer you to <hi>Markhams</hi> master piece, page 76. by him called the general cramp, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the staggers in Cattle.</head>
            <p>THe cause of this disease, is blood offending in quaintity, and heat in the fore part of his head, as appears by the signs, for he looks very red about the eyes, and casts his head backwards doth reel and stagger.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is.</head>
               <p>First let him blood in the veins on the top of his nose, or in the eye veins under his eyes. The take one dram of fine powder of Peper, and a quarter of a pint of white wine vineger, mix them well together, and being made blood warm, pour it into his nostrils, into each alike portion, and let him go to meat, the cure is done, <hi>probatum est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the rot in Cattle.</head>
            <p>THis disease may be taken by drinking bad water, or for lack of water: Also by feeding on young tender grass that is alwayes wet; by reason of continuall rain, and inundation of waters; As it was in the year, 1648, and also in 1655. These two years, by reason of intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate weather, adn want of food; caused a Rot
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:206326:31"/>amongst Cattle: and so many dyed, that some men were impoverished by their loss, whereof many are come over into this Istand-in hope to recover their losses; and remain little better then Servants to their hard and griping <hi>Cheshire</hi>-land lords, but this is not my task.</p>
            <p>The rot in Cattle is of three sorts, whereof, two may rather be called Consumptions then Rots: The first is a dry rot of Consumption of the lights, with a continuall coughing.</p>
            <p>The second is a Consumption of the liver, and blood, by flat worms, such as are in some sheeps livers called flouks.</p>
            <p>The third is a wet rot how beit, I will speak of the two later first, and then of the other.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Signs are.</head>
                  <p>In the water rot, the Cattle have great bellies full of water: which you may hear chink, if you put your hand to his belly and shake it sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, three or four times together: Also some will have poughs under their jawes full of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his hair will look old and be soft, and the ends of it will be small, and of a dun colour, and his body lean and weak, scarce able to rise.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The cure is.</head>
                  <p>To slit the skin in the upper part of his daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lap, two fingers straight downward, then open the sides a finger breadth, and a finger lenghth down. Then take nine green leaves of mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, &amp; bind them with a thread together, and put it down into the would, and let an other thread hang down without, that you may thereby
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:206326:32"/>draw it up an down the wound, every two or three dayes once or twice. Use this the space of fifteen or sixteen dayes, and within a while ye shall see it swell, and at lenghth it will putrifie and stink, run and rot away skin and all; some will swell before they run of water, which is avoyding so much corruption cleanseth the beast, and maketh him whole again: And give him the juice of Saxifrige in drink, <hi>Len. Mascal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others do peg his dawlap with black Helebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie-root, as I taught for the murren; and many do very well thereby. Also some Illeterate Oxe-leaches make this peging a Catholical me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, others put a handfull of spear Grass-tops chopt with salt into the said wound, and many do amend thereby, others put the green stalkes and leaves of master-wort (which they call Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-grass) into the said wound, and it does well, often proved. And now in the close, and end of these take my way as followeth.</p>
                  <p>First I clip away the hair of the dowlap from the lower corner (which hangs to his knees) straight upwards a finger length, and two inches in breadth. Then I slit the skin cross wayes, a finger length above the hard corner thereof, till I cut just through one side, but cut no deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then one skin. The with my finger or a knife, I part the two skins asunder, one finger length upwards his head, and one finger length downwards towards his breast. Then I take five or six trounchins of mug-wort stalkes being green, each one a finger long, and as big as a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:206326:32"/>Goose-quill: tye them fast together with a strong double thread, just in the middle; and leave the two ends of the thread, each of them three inches long to spare: Then put this bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of stalkes so tyed into the wound laying it along the skin, cross the slit: Then stitch the lips of the wound together, with one stitch on each side in the middle, and let one end of the spare thread (wherewith the bundle is bound) hang above your stitch, and the other below; to the end you may stir your bundle upwards and downwards once a day, as you were taught in the beginning of this cure. Now I use the stalkes of master-wort leaves if I can get them in the room of mug-wort if I cannot get it.</p>
                  <p>This wound will run and avoid a brown sani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous water like lye, till the beast be found, and then it will yield laudable quitter called <hi>pus,</hi> then the cure is perfect, <hi>probatum est.</hi> But you shall have some Cattle with great water bellies, which admit not of this cure: because the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is either in the great paunch, or in the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of his belly amongst his guts: in so great abundance, that these foresaid medicines do not help at all.</p>
                  <p>If the water be in his great paunch, ye may know by his continual sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wring: and your cure is as for the flux of the belly taught before,</p>
                  <p>If the hollow of his belly be full of water, you may know by the stinking thereof, as is said before. And the best remedy is to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:206326:33"/>in the flanke in the mid-way between the side of his belly, and the middle thereof: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Navel of a Cow and her uddern; but beware of the milk veins, and so of an Oxe or Bullock beware of those great veins in his sides under his belly: they are called the spur-veins in a Horse. I say beware of them, because your incision will be somewhat near to them. Make your orafice or hole in the belly no biggen then to receive a Goose-quill; and thereby loose out the water, two or three quarts at a time, and so the next day, and then a day or two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, and draw water again till you have all: which you may know by the lankness of your beasts belly, and his having more mind to eat then before. You had best cast your beast to make the issue at first, and then you may put in a quill, or the small end of a glister-pipe which is best of all; there is no danger in this way of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, but of cutting too deep, and by that means spoyling his guts, there is great bladders of clear water growing on the livers of some of these beasts; which when they break, the water falleth down into the belly: and having no pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage out causeth the beasts belly to swell, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ls so full, that he can scarce breath, and at last kills him, if remedy be not found. These bladders do make great se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts in the liver where they are: yea, some times wear it through, and then the cure is hard, and few escape death, other wayes this cure never fails.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:206326:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Signs of the Rot, with Floukes in their livers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>These Cattle go softly, though they be young and look well; their hair looks old, is <hi>tantum,</hi> and they are weak; and the tops of their noses are alwayes dry. If these signs follow a wet and cold Summer, and their feeding have been in cold and wet land, then be sure it is the Rot and Floukes in their livers, as some Rotten sheep have.</p>
                  <p>The cure for ought I know, (or could ever learn) is yet to find. But they dye as Rotten sheep, when grass begins to fail, and they must seed on dry meat, as hay and straw, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When one of these beasts is dead, ye shall have little or no blood in him: but his flesh will look white and fair like slaughter meat. But if you cut and slash the liver, you shall see the great veins and pipes thereof, full of red flat worms; some of them as broad as an English groat: and in fashion like a liver. These remain quick long after the beast is dead: yea, I have seen them alive when the beast hath been dead a whole day. If there be any medicine to destroy these ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min and not the beast; It is to give him strong brine half a pint at a time nine mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but let their grass be good that blood may increase, else the cure is lost.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Signs of the dry Rot, or lung-sore.</head>
               <p>This is a grievous disease, and few recover; except they have help in time. A beast that hath this infermity will wax lean and pine away; he hath a common coughing and housing, so that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:206326:34"/>he will hold forth his tongue, and cough, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a quarter of an hour together: he will stand much and eat little, and wax hollow and thin of body; the hair on his back doth stand upright, and his skin cleaves fast to his back and ribs. Then he is very near spent and hard to recover, for his lights are corrupted, and wasted either in whole or in part. I have seen the one half of a beasts lights all full of quitter, or bealing as the vulgar say; yea, as bad corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as even I see in a boyl or sellon: yea some will have all the signs of this dry Rot, but cough not; in this case I see one dye, and when he was slit open his lights were hard and gritly as though they had been half sand.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The cure is.</head>
                  <p>In the first place so soon as you perceive your beast to cough or hoarse, make no stay to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy him if possible; for delays are dangerous. First take a quantity of the juice of leeks, with so much Salit oyl, and mix it with a pint and half of Wine, and give it him fasting: use this nine mornings together. Also ye shall pierce one of his ears with a little bodkin, and make many holes therein; then ye shall put into the said holes, the burnt-root of some hazell-tree. Some use to setter, or rowl their dowlaps with master-wort (which they call Setter grass: or, Diascorides his Heleborie.) They bruise it in a morter, and put it into the dowlap, as is shewed before with mug-wort. But the best way to rowel with either of these herbs; is as I taught
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:206326:34"/>before for the wet Rot: for it doth operate speedily. Also our vulgar Oxe-leeches speak of the lungs of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me Cattle being grown to their sides; and the signs they give to know it, are the same with the former: only this much more is said, that if he be lung-grown, he will then lather sometimes at his mouth in holding it commonly open, and runeth of water both at his mouth and nose. These signs are common to the lungs sick before shewed, and signifie no other disease; and when a beast is in this case the cure is hard, if not unpossible. But the best way I know is to kill him, if he be in so good state as to make meat on, if not you may bestow money and paines to prove the force of medcines; and try practice. The usual remedies are as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Take a handful of lung-wort roots bruise them small in a morter, put to them a quart of Ale or Beer, wring out the juice, and give it to the beast, do this four or five mornings together, but give him no meat till two hours after. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do take a quantity of figs, with a handful of Isop bruised together, then boile them a little in a quart of Ale or Beer, then strain it and give it to your beast two or three mornings fasting, but no meat till two hours after. Also take a good handful of pansis, or hearts ease, and stamp it with a quart of Ale or Beer, and then strain it, and give it to the beast three or four mornings, and use him as aforesaid. These are counted special good against the said disease;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:206326:35"/>yet one more and I have done, it is much in use in some Countries. They cut away a round piece of skin in the dewlap, and then with their finger and a little salt, make a hole downwards two inches or more; and then fils the said hole with red garlick stamped, and plaistered thereon with nettles stamped with salt, or with yorrow and salt mixt together with vineger: Then ye shall give him this following. Take of Fenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek, of Turmerick, and of lung-wort herb stamp all these together in a morter, and mix them with a quart or more of strong Ale or Beer, and give it to your beast; use it eight or nine mornings, or more as need is: and it will help if he be not too far gon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the cough in old Cattle, and Calves.</head>
            <p>THe cough in Cattle of above two years old, is accompanied with infection of the lungs, for the most part; especially if he begin with a shrill hoarsing, or whiesing in his throat, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most like a fute, or whistle, as fugh, fugh. Then be sure it is from infection of the lights: except he have wanted water long, or eaten much Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley in the ears. Some get the cough by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much heat and sudden cold; and then they cough loud and strongly, and sometime get up flegme as people do, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But your calves of half a year old, and so forwards to two years of age, but specially the younger, get a cough for want of water: and the fault is in their owners for the most part; for when they wean their Calves either from their dams, or cease to give
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:206326:35"/>them milk, or whay to drink; then they put them into some graft or yard of good grass, but bad water: or the way to it so bad, that the Calves (being young and fearful) dare not venter to go down to the hole, or pit where it is; but only get some refreshment by dewie mornings; yet not wherewith to cool their thirst, and so heat and dryness causeth a hot rhume to distill from their heads, which falling down upon the wind pipe and lights, causeth a whising cough, which appears commonly in the month of <hi>September.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure for old beasts.</head>
               <p>Take a pound of Hysope, steep it in two quarts of water, then bruise it very small, mix it with barley flower and so make him to swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, and after pour the water, (that the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sope was steeped and sodden in) into his throat; and with often doing this some are cured.</p>
               <p>Some give two spoonfuls of pure Tar with a pint of new churn-milk, warm out of the churn, if that cannot be got take warm milk new milked, mix the milk and Tar very well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and give it the beast in the morning fasting, and let him fast two hours after. Use this nine mornings together, and it helpeth, often proved. <hi>G. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Calves cough (as is before said) give them strong Ale or Beer, wherein Centorie hath been steeped twelve hours, give it eight or nine dayes, or as you see cause, L. M.</p>
               <p>Others take for each Calve a handful of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow-fearn,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:206326:36"/>and beat it very small in a morter, or dish, then put thereto a pint of new churn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milk, for each calve so much, stir it well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and give each his part in the morning fasting, do this four or five mornings together, as need is, it is a speedy remedy often proved.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Discription of the Fearn.</head>
                  <p>This small herb, is much like unto <hi>Osmund</hi> or water Fearn; but the leaves are more jaged, and are very thick set on the stalkes: but in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as fearn leaves are: yet the leaf with all his jags is broadest at the bottom, near to the great stream, and ends in a point as fearn doth, it growes in a thick bush; broad at the root, and narrow at the top, and for the most part one in a place. The colour is a black green: it hath flowers of colour like blew and red mixt; and when the flowers fade the seed growes, and is ripe in <hi>August;</hi> the seeds are in little pods, five or six in one, they are thin flat ones. These seeds spring up the first May after they fall, and that year the leaves trail, and spread on the earth, but the next year it growes up to a bush, flowers, seeds, and dyes root an all. It growes in barren wet meadowes, and in corrohs at bog-sides, and is noysome weed to the grass, so much for the discription.</p>
                  <p>It is good for use being green, else not; and he that takes notice where it growes, may find the young ones gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en all the winter. But the best of all cures for the cough in young Cattle; if the lights be not infected, is as followeth.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:206326:36"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>First, cut a piece of skin in the dowlap of your beast, begin to cut two fingers breadth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the hard knot where the two skins grow together: and cut till you come below the knot; so that the skin cut may hang down to the beasts knee like a tongue, and so let it remain. Then give your beast one ounce of the whitest and of prest leek roots, such as you eat; beat them very small, and mix them with a pint of Ale, or Beer, make it blood warm and give it to him in the morning fasting, use this four or five dayes together. If you want leeks take Garlick, but then boile it one walm or two. This done you shall perceive your beast to cough less, and less every day, so that with one moneth or five weeks he will be perfectly whole, often proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Cud of a beast lost.</head>
            <p>THe Cud of a beast, is a substance of slimy froath, and chewed grass mixt; it lies in the top of his stomack: all times but when he is at rest, and chewing it; but then it lyes on a lump in the side of his mouth. By the chewing of this Cud, the meat which he eateth is digested: and if he loose it he will not chew at all: but mourn, and pine away, if remedy be not found. He may loose it by coughing suddenly when he is chewing; or by hasty driving at the same time, or by long sickness. The signs that it is lost are, as before is shewed; which are the more infallible if he be free from any disease besides. Also the grass he hath eaten will come
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:206326:37"/>through him not half digested; or else dry and bake together in the stomack, and cause a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git there, and costiveness in the whole body.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The remedies are.</head>
               <p>Some do use to take part of the Cud out of the mouth of an other beast, which is of like nature; as if it be a Cow that wants her Cud, take some of the Cud of another Cow, and give it her to swallow down, and by that means she will do well again: and so the like of other beasts, <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The way I use is, to catch the other Cow or Oxe while they are chewing, before he loose his Cud down, and take some part thereof, out of the side of his mouth, where I see the lump lyeth; then I wrap that part in fine sweet hay, or sweet grass, a little quantity, and put it so wraped between the beasts jaw teeth that wanteth his quid; so by chewing that hay or grass, he will immediately chew his Cud, and do well, often proved.</p>
               <p>Some take a piece of sowre leaven, and put it into the beasts mouth to chew, and he will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by recover again: Also when a beast hath lost his Cud clean, ye may give him lome, or clay of a wall mixt with urine, and make him swallow it; or take the crum of brown bread, and mix it with a little salt, and therewith rub and chafe the tongue of the beast; But if your beast be grown weak with this disease, take forth his tongue, and with a fine lance let him blood, in the vein which is in the middle thereof, on the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:206326:37"/>under side, and give him some part of an other beasts Cud as is taught, or for want thereof, rub his mouth and tongue with oat-meal and salt, and put some between his jaw teeth to set him on chewing, and it fails not to help.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Worm in the tail of Beasts.</head>
            <p>This disease which they call the worm in the tail of a beast is a sharp sanious water, like to lye in colours, it lyeth at the top of the fan of the tail, or rather falleth down from the back to that place; but however it frets away the flesh, yea and the bone also, and by little and little creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up into the back, and makes it wax lean, and crooked: Also the teeth are loose, and the tail is soft at the top of the fan, and the skin thereof hallow, as though it had no bone in it; yea, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times the bone is almost fretted a sunder, and the beast becometh lean, ill-favoured of body and weak, and if remedy be not found pineth away.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is.</head>
               <p>You shall take the tail in your hand, and feel the softest place, above the knot, where the long hair of the fan groweth, and a little above that place on the inside of the tail, ye shall slit the skin with a sharp knife two inches down right, so done, take a quantity of bruised Garlick and salt mixt together, and bind it fast to that place, and let it so remain till it do fall away of it self, and so the beast shall recover and be well again, saith <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:206326:38"/>
            <head>Goring of a beast to help.</head>
            <p>THis sorance is a thrust, or push with the horn of an other beast, whereby the skin is broken and a great wound made, often bigger within then it appeareth outwardly. Also, there is an other sort of goring, which the vulgar call panching, but are herein deceived, for a beast cannot be said to be panched, except the great panch be broken. But this goring I now speak of, is when one beast is pushed or hurt with the horn of another, or by any other accident in the thin part of the belly, so that the inner rym is broken, or torn, yet the outmost skin remains hole, and sound. This is a dangerous bound, for it looseth the small guts out of the belly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the skin, so that it hangs down on a great lump, in some as big as a bag of two gallons, and some less; you may know it from a great imposthume, because this comes on a sudden, and is soft in feeling; but the other ariseth softly, and is alwayes hard in feeling.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure.</head>
               <p>The remedy for this goring is by incision, putting up the guts, and sowing up the breach with two seams, the one within and the other without the belly, as thou shalt be taught, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore attend with diligence to the instructions following. First provide a warm house to keep thy beast in for nine or ten dayes: Also let there be some beam over the house, about two yards from the ground, and about half a yard from the wall of the house, in a place where you may
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:206326:38"/>have perfect light, yet free from wind; this done, provide a strong hemp rope, that will hold your beast to hang by the hinder feet. Then bring your beast into the house, and with your hand feel where the breach is in his belly; which for the most part is above the place where the guts hang in the skin, and sometimes there is a great breach very easie to be found, and in some beasts it is but small, not easie to be found; yet if you can find it while the beast stands, it is the best: which done, clip off the hair with your scisers, to the end you may cut the skin near that place, as discretion shall lead you. Then having good store of straw in the house, cast your beast thereon, and tye his two hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most legs together with the rope you provided before, tye them a little above the dew-clawes, and put straw or cloaths between the rope and his legs, to the end you hurt not the great si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news, and so lame your beast. This done, draw his hindmost legs up to the beam I told you of before; or so high till his shoulder may rest at the flour of the house, then make your rope fast, so that he may hang till your operation be done: tye his two fore-feet together, and hold them still, and hold his head fast, and put straw between his back and the wall, that he may hang as easie as impossible: Then clip away the hair where thou will cut the skin, and with a sharp knife made for gelding and inscision only; slit the skin length-wise the beast, make your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scision six or eight inches long, but beware you
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:206326:39"/>cut not the guts, which in this case lye between the skin and the flesh; then put up his guts with your hand gently, and take heed of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or crushing them; if the breach be but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and narrow, you had need take the more care and hold them up to the breach with one hand, and with the fourth finger of the other put them up, still following the rope, putting that in first which came out last, till thou hast put all the said guts into his belly again, which being put in, will fall into their true place. This done, Take a broad, or a square-pointed needle, so big, that the eye thereof may receive a double thread, so that you may sow with four threads twisted together; then begin your work on this wise. First, put the fourth finger of your left hand into the wound, and hold up the edge thereof between your finger and your thumb; then put your needle into the edge of the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken flesh, near the upper end thereof, and guide your needle so, that it may take the one half of the thickness of that flesh, and also the thin film or skin that is on the inner side; so draw your needle through, and then in like manner, take up the inner film, and half the thickness of the flesh on the other side the wound: then draw the lips of the wound close together with your thread, and tye it gently to remain, but not very hard, neither draw very rashly, for fear of breaking out your stitches: then keeping your finger between the beast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> guts and the needle, stitch up all the breach, drawing the lips of the wound close to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:206326:39"/>so that it may be a fine seam, yet not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard, for that may cause the flesh to inflame, swell, and corrupt. This seam being sown, and the thread made fast that it get not loose, then sow the out side of the wound also, and take some stitches a good way from the edges of the sore on each side, to the end the seam may be the stronger; but all this while beware of stitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beasts guts to his side. This done, lade out the blood and water which is in the loose skin, with your hand, and having ready half a pound of mealted butter, pour it therein, but not so hot as to scald; stir it with your hand to every place of the sore, the stitch up the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most skin, one stitch in a place, through both the edges of the loose skin, and draw them close together; so tye up that stitch: then take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in like manner, one inch from the first, and so on, till the silt you cut be all stitcht up, and by leaving an inch, or some more between each stitch, there will be good room left for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to issue out, if that seam do hang lowest of the wound; if it do not, then with your pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knife or lancet, make an issue in the most depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent place, for the wound to close it self by, make it an inch and quarter long. Then untye your ropes, and loose down your beast; and with your bare hands rub and chafe his legs, till they be hot: get to each leg one, and be sure to rub the sinews well, because they are benum'd, and almost dead with hanging, and must be recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this labour of your hands. This done,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:206326:40"/>boulster up your beast with straw, and let him sit and rest an hour, but first give him a quart of strong Ale or Beer made warm, and an ounce of the fine powder of Aniseeds therein. If your beast rise not of his own accord at the hours end, then cause him to rise, and help him, if need be; then take a strong twill-sheet, or any other strong linen cloath, and wrap it about his body, the bight under his belly, and pin or sow the two sides together on his back, let it be wrapt close. This done, give him meat, and keep him in the house fourteen dayes; give him sufficient water twice a day, keep his stall clean, and make his bed soft with straw, and once in two days bathe the sore with moulten butter. Open the issue with your finger, and stroak the skin that is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low with your hand, to drive the quitter that is under it down to the issue. If it be in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, anoint it with Tar, to keep slies from of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, and at the end of fourteen dayes, let him go abroad, and have a care that his fellows abuse him not at the first, and he will do well, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten proved.</p>
               <p>But if your beast be so goared, that his guts come out, trale after him, and some of them be broken; or so hurt, that they are like to perish; then the cure is hard and difficult, yet not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes impossible, if your wit be acute, and your hand active. But your best course in this case is, if your beast be fat to kill him: but if he be not in so good state as to make meat on, then take this course which will hardly fail the cure, if he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:206326:40"/>be not very weak, and far spent. The cure is, you must find a convenient place to hang him by the two hindmost feet, and cut open the skin as you see need, and put in his guts, as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cure, till you come to the broken place. Then if there be any torn along the guts, or else jaged, that may not be stitched together, for it will not grow: neither will that which is black, cold, and dead; in which cases thou must do this. First, lay the two broken ends that should grow together, the one a little over the other in your hand; then cut them both off at once with a pair of sharp scissers, so that the new-cut ends may be joyned close together; but first cut the two broken ends off close to the mid-read and cast them away, then with a fine needle &amp; thread, or silk, stitch the two new cut ends together, so that they may gently meet, and not be strained; begin first to stitch at the mid-rise, and so round about the gut till you come to the same place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and there make fast your thread: But in your stitching remember this, that, as you must not draw your seam too hard, for fear of crush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that tender skin; neither must you leave it too slack, for fear the dung issue out; for if you miss either way, you are sure to fail in your cure. When you have stitcht the gut ends together, with a fine and thick seam, and wiped away the blood and dirt clean; then anoint it with hogs grease and the juice of Cumfray mixt. This done, put the guts into his belly, and stitch up the breach, first the inner-side, then the middle,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:206326:41"/>and then dress with moulten butter, and stitch up the out most skin as is taught before, and use the beast as in the former cure: only do this more; that is, give him the juice of Cumfray in strong Ale or Beer to drink, and if he dung and stink two or three dayes, there is no doubt of the cure. But in both these cures be sure of good help, and be quick at thy work, and careful withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Goring in any other part besides the belly to help.</head>
               <p>FIrst search the wound to the bottome and sides, and if it be very large within, and have but a narrow orafice, (as often they have,) then cut the mouth of the sore wider; to the end you may put tents into the wound. This done, take one ounce of common Turpentine, two ounces of hogs grease purified, and four ounces of Tar, and one scruple of verdigrease in fine powder, mix them very well together till they be a perfect salve; then tent and dress your beast therewith once a day as you were taught for the imposthume, and you shall have a perfect cure in a short time, this I have often proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>For a cut with a weapon or hurt.</head>
            <p>BE sure to search the sore to the bottom, and tent it with rags of clean linnen cloath, or fine flax dipt in the foresaid salve made warm; use it once or twice a day, and it is a special cure. But if you fear the tents will not abide in the wound, but work out with the beasts motion; then you are to put a small string to each side of the wound: I mean through the skin at the lips
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:206326:41"/>of the wound with your needle, and tye the tents until your time of dressing, and then untye them till you have renewed your tents; use it thus till it need no tents, but to be anointed on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and it helps, often proved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>To heal the Closh, or Foundre, in the feet of Cattel.</head>
            <p>THis soreance in the feet of cattel, is taken by some cold after a great heat, or by some vehement travel or running, which hath stirred the blood, so that it goeth down to the feet, like the founder of a horse feet; yea, much worse, when this doth happen to a beast, it will sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly visit the hoof, and you may feel it very hot, and paineth the beast so, that he will not suffer you to touch that place, nor crush the foot. Some have the heated blood lying in their legs, some their fetter-locks, and some in their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterns, at the top of the hoof round about, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing those parts to swell, and you may feel it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hot: also some will have their feet swoln so, that their claws will straddle, and if you rub be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his claws with a hair rope, sawing it to and fro, you shall see a yellow cork or core arise near his heel, which some call the fowle, others the kibe; the fowle, when in the forepart of the foot; and the kibe, in the heel. But all chese are one and the same sarance, onely some of a more mild nature, and others more violent, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the beast is, either cholerick, or melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly; and so will the cure be either facile, or difficult. But the most dangerous of all found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:206326:42"/>and hardest to cure, is that which breaks out with deep holes in the joynts, just above the hoof. This is a most rebellious sore, and many beasts belamed thereby.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure of all these are;</head>
               <p>First, if the legs be gorged with blood, you shall rub and chafe them with your hands very hard, to heat the blood; then raise and scarifie them very well, with the point of a sharp pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knife, or lancet; but beware of cutting too deep, for fear of veins and sinews, yet make him bleed well: do the like below the dew-claws, at the top of the hoof, if need be. I use to pare off the ring, which riseth about the hoof at the top thereof, full of hot chafed blood, I pare it even with the hoof, hair and all, whether it be beast or horse, and let it bleed well; then take net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and stamp them very small, and mix there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with salt and vineger, and some gross lint, or fine flax to make it stick together; then spread it on a lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cloath, and lay it all over the new-cut places, and renew it twice a day, and it helps: but in all cures of the feet, you must keep your cattle that have this sorance in the house, and their sore feet dry, else the cure will be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long: but if the founder be broaken out in the joynt above the hoof, and have deep holes in it, then you must make tents of lint, and rolling them in the said salve, tent the holes once a day, and plaister them as the other; and when the sores cease to be rebellious, and begin to heal and dry, you may heal them up with a salve
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:206326:42"/>made of four ounces of Hogs grease, and two ounces of unslackt lime, well mixt and beaten together to a perfect salve: if you cannot get unslackt lime, then buy serice two ounces, and one scruple of verdegrease, and make it into a salve, as before; then spread it on a cloath, and lay it on the sore, renew it once a day, till the foot be whole. And for sores between the claws, which they call the kibe, Take a hair rope, and anoint it with Hogs grease, or butter, and rub very well with it between the claws, in sawing to and fro, the foot being held fast: this done, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint it with soft grease, and if you see any cork therein, let it so remain till it be ripe, and the edges thereof rise, and divide it from the sound flesh, so that you may thrust it out with your finger; which done, rub it with a rope gently, as aforesaid, and lay a plaister thereon of Hogs grease and verdegrease, mixt and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to a perfect salve, and keep the foot dry, as is before taught, renewing the plaister once a day, till it be whole, <hi>probatum est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Warts on the feet of Cattle:</head>
            <p>CAttle will have warts on their feet sometimes, they grow between the dew-claws and the heel, and are long teats, much like the pains on a horses legs, but very sore, and cause the beast to halt much, and go cripling, if they be on the hinder-feet, as commonly they are.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>First, cast your beast, end tye his legs fast, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:206326:43"/>he neither hurt you nor himself; then take a pair of fire-tongs, being made red-hot, burn those teats, laying on pitch, and making it fry with your hot tongs, or some other hot iron necessary for that work: the better you burn them, the sooner they will heal; yet burn not through the skin, for fear you touch the sinews and lame the beast.</p>
               <p>This having cauterised those teats, and made their roots raw, your next work is, to make a plaister of the aforesaid salve, and lay thereon, renewing it once a day, and keep it dry till it be whole. <hi>Often proved.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Knees of Cattle swoln.</head>
            <p>IF the knees of any beast be swoln, ye shall first bathe them with white vineger; then take vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, millet, and linseed, beaten to powder, and a little honey and water, and so mix them, and bind that to his knees; and if there be any inflammation of humour, you must scarrifie it with the point of a sharp knife, to let out the chafed blood: then apply to it nettles beaten with salt and vineger, till it be well, which will not be long If it be well scarified in time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the blood putrifie, which if it do, then the cure is, to lay it to a Cataplasme, made of the fine powder of flax-seed, fenugreek, and barley-meal, boiled in honied-water, to ripen it <hi>t</hi> and when it is ripe, then lance it, lose out the curru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and heal it with tarr, turpentine, and Hogs grease, as is taught before. <hi>This is well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:206326:43"/>
            <head>Of the Spaven on the Hough.</head>
            <p>THis sorance I call the spaven, not as though an ox or cow had any sorance so called, but because it is so like that sorance on a horses legs; for the signs are the same, with that they call the through-spaven: for it is a soft swelling, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on both sides the hough, and seems as though it went through the same; but for the most part, the swelling is most on the inside, and least on the outside; but on which fide soever it is, the beast goeth lame therewith; and if it be not help'd in time, it will wax hard, like the bone-spaven on a horse, and so become incurable.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure, if found, is as followeth.</head>
               <p>First, cut a good long slash in the highest place of the sorance, along the leg; but beware of veins and sinews; then there will appear to you, next under the skin, a soft spungious flesh, like as it were small bladders blown full of wind, which you are to draw up with your hand, and cut them off close to the good flesh; then dress the sore with nettles, and a little salt beaten together, to draw out the corrupt blood, and after heal it with the healing salve, prescribed for cuts and hurts. <hi>Proved.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>For sinews stiff and shrinking.</head>
            <p>FOR this sorence, you are to chafe and rub his legs, and knees, or hams with salt and oyl mixt, till it be well, or rub and chafe them very well with nerve oyl once a day, till they be well. The best of all ointments for the sinewes and joynts of any beasts, is patch grease, with which
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:206326:44"/>ye must rub and chase the sinews very well, and hold a hot iron against it, to melt the ointment, and cause it to sink in: do this once a day, for three or four days, then once in three days, till it be well.</p>
            <p>If the sinews are benum'd with cold, by lying in a bog, or otherwise. Then you are to rub his limbs and body very well with dry straw, till he be warm and dry: then rub his sinews with the foresaid oyl, and chafe them well, and make a sire near the beast or horse to warm him; also give him two or three quarts of strong Beer or Ale, made blood-warm, to warm and comfort him. Do this, and he will soon recover and rise, if his heart be not perished with lying over long in the cold mire or water. Often proved:</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to make the foresaid Oyl.</head>
               <p>Take a peck of shoe-makers patches, those which they pare off their leather and shoes, and one pint of Train oyl, and one pound of sheeps suet rendered. Put these two, and the pieces of leather into two gallons of fair water, and boil them one quarter of an hour: then take it off the fire, and let it stand to cool; and when it is cold, the fat will lie on the top of the water: then take it off, and put it into some earthen pot to keep for your use. If you do not use it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you had best to purifie it, and keep it in a close pot, till you have need. It is a very present remedy for either man or beast, whose sinews be in any wise hurt or stiff. Often proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:206326:44"/>
            <head>To heal Scabs and Gauls in Cattle.</head>
            <p>IF your Cattle be scabby, your best way is, to wash and rub them very well with oxe piss made warm; rub off the scabs, and when they are dry, anoint them with fresh butter, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten garlick, well mixt together. Do this three times, two dayes between eath time, and it help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Mange on Cattle.</head>
            <p>THis disease is so like to the mange on a dog, that I can give it no other name; and I have no Authour that speaks of it, nor many more; and therefore I give it a name like it self.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Signs of this Soranet are.</head>
               <p>It beginneth commonly on the neck of Calves, or other young Cattle, with small moyst hurtls, and the skin is wet as though the beast did sweat, and when that moisture is dry it baketh hard to the skin, and is of a hoary colour; and the next day the moisture issueth out again, and dryeth as is said: and so becometh a hoary scab, or scurf; and if it be not remedied in time it will spread all over the beast and kill him in time. Yea, many Calves of a year old dye thereof: and all for their masters want of skill and will to remedy them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The remedy is.</head>
               <p>First to let them blood in the neck vein, and let them bleed well; that is, till you see the blood turn from black and thick, to red and thin. Then take a Gallon of Ox, or Cow piss, and put therein four or five handfulls of Goose
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:206326:45"/>dung new made, mix it very well together, then strain, or gather out the dung with your hand, and keep the piss. Then warm some of it, and therewith wash your beast where the mange is; bath it well to soften the hard scurf, and with a Cury-comb, or some other fit instrument, scrape up the scurf clean from the skin, till it look raw, and be ready to bleed; then wash it again and so leave it for that time. Wash and rub off the hard scurf thrice a week, till the scurf dye, and the skin continue clean. But if the weather be cold when you wash, as oft it is, then you must keep them in the warm house till they be dry. And give them meat good store, for the better you keep them, the sooner you shall have your desired cure, often proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Flowing of the Gall, or yellowes.</head>
            <p>THe flowing of the Gall in Oxe or other beast, is occasioned by overmuch choller, which fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the gall so full that it flowes, and runs all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the body, and so causeth the yellowes, or Jaundise.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The signs thereof are.</head>
               <p>Yellowness of the eyes within, the skin is yellow, and full of small dust, and scales all over the body, and his ears abound with ear-wax; so that sometimes all the flaps will be wet on the inner-side, almost to the top of the ear, and the beast will refuse to eat, and pine away, and at last dye, if remedy be not found.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The remedy is.</head>
               <p>Take a new-laid hens egg, make a hole in the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:206326:45"/>top thereof, and pour out the white, then take fine powder of pepper, and hard soot of a chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney beaten to fine powder, and with equal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of soot and pepper fill up the Egg-shell, and mix them very well with the yelke; then add to it so much honey as to fill the Egg-shell very full; and so put the Egg into the beasts mouth, and make him swallow it shell an all: and before he go from your hand, give him half a pint of Urine made warm, do this three morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings together, and it is a perfect cure, often proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>For any beast that cannot piss.</head>
            <p>IF Oxe or other beast do tremble and stamp when they should piss, and do it but by drops, or none at all; Then ye shall give him warm water, wherein wheat bran hath been scalded to drink, and it will help him, <hi>Maschal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my cure is, to take two green Onion blades, and beat them small, then put to them so beaten a quart, or three pints of new Beer or Ale, and give it to the beast with a horn, do this three mornings fasting, and it helpeth often proved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Hide bound in a beast to help.</head>
            <p>THis grievance is so called, because the hide sticks fast to his back and sides; so that you cannot pinch it up with your fingers. This grief comes commonly by bad keeping and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, it doth sore trouble and torment the beast and makes his hair to stair, and look old, and the beast to look wanderous il-favouredly.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:206326:46"/>
               <head>The cure is.</head>
               <p>First let the beast blood, and let him bleed well, that is till you see it alter from black to more red; Then give him of long Peper, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nugreek, and Aniseed, of each one peniworth, beaten to very fine powder, and boiled in a quart of strong Beer, when it is boiled ad to it one ounce of Sugar, and one head of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, finely pil'd and beaten small, mix these well together, and give it to your beast blood-warm in the morning fasting, three dayes together; each day so much, and keep him well. Also you must rub and chafe his back and sides very well with your hands, anointing it all along the Ridge, and on both sides with Salit oyl; rub it exceedingly, and pull up the skin with your hands to loose it, and hold a hot Iron over it, to cause the oyl to sink in. But if you can get Patch grease for this use, it is excellent, do this four or five times, alwayes two or three dayes between, and it helpeth without fail.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Lice on Cattle to kill.</head>
            <p>IT is generally agreed amongst all Artists, that Cattle become lowfie by taking some Surfet, or cold after a great heat and rain: But for my part I judge the cause to be unclean keeping in the house, and mustie unsound food, and many times for want of food in due time. This stands with reason; for, if a beast be never so lowfie, give him good hay enough, and some oats, or grass sufficient, and he will shake them off, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other help.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:206326:46"/>
               <head>The Remedy is,</head>
               <p>Take a gallon of fair water, and set it on the fire in a kettle, and put therein as much of the fine powder of white Arseneck, as will lie on an English Six-pence; boyl it a walm or two, then take it from the fire, and while it is yet reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able hot, wash the beasts neck and shoulders, and all other places where the lice are, in shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or parting the hair with your fingers, that the water may come to the bottom: Do this twice, and keep your beast tyed in the house, till his hair be dry, and it helpeth. Often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Another as well proved by me.</head>
               <p>Take quick-silver one peny worth, and four ounces of Hogs-grease clarified, and one dram of brimstone in fine powder; mix all these in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients very well together, so long, till you can see none of the quick-silver at all: then clip away a little hair from their horn-roots, and anoint that place with some of this ointment. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so clip away a spot of hair on the top of his shoulders, and another on the lowest part of his dowlap, and anoint these places with the said ointment, and it will kill all the lice on his body. <hi>Probatum est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Lice to kill.</head>
               <p>OR, take a shread of new woollen cloath, of an inch and half broad, and so long, as to reach about his neck: Dress it with the oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and stitch it close about his neck like a coller, and so let it remain for the space of a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:206326:47"/>moneth, and it will kill all the lice of his whole bopy. <hi>Probatum est.</hi> My Masters, the old ox-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches teach many wayes to kill lice; but I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways use these of mine own, because they are easily got, and never fail to do the work.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Worms in cattle or calves.</head>
            <p>CAttle will oft have worms in their bellies, but especially calves, which will annoy them much, and at length kill them, if remedy be not found in time.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The signs are these.</head>
               <p>Ye shall see them run up and down, and not stand or abide long in one place, and sometimes lie down, shake, and quiver, and straight-wayes up again, and about, and some will hold their heads oft towards their sides.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Remedy is,</head>
               <p>Take a handful of tansie, and a little worm-wood; beat them very small, and mix them with sweet milk, and so give each beast a pint in the morning fasting, three dayes together. If to a calf, give but half a pint at a time.</p>
               <p>If ye cannot get tansie, wormwood will serve alone; or, Take of the juice of Hore-hound, beaten and stampt, with a quantity of leek-blades; make it in pellets as big as wall-nuts, with sweet butter, and so give it two or three to a big beast at a time, and one to a calf.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Loosness of teeth in cattle.</head>
            <p>IF the teeth of any beast be loose, and yet have no fret in his tail, ye shall cut an inch and a half of the end of his tail, and let him
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:206326:47"/>bleed well there, it is a present remedy; or you may scarifie his gums with the point of a sharp knife, and make them bleed; then wash them with white-wine vineger and salt mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and rub them well therewith two or three times, and it helpeth. Often proved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Bones broken or loose; or, sinews to knit.</head>
            <p>IF any bone of a beast be broken, or out of joynt; First, cause an Artist to set them in their right places, and to roll the fracture fast; then take off the herb cumfrey, bruise some of the leafs and roots thereof with a little honey, and lay it too plaister-wayes, and when it is dry and hard, then make a new plaister, and lay to it.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>Take yarrow and some cumfrey leafs, and stamp them small with swines grease, end plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterwayes lay them to. This will knit bones and sinews also.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Purging of eattle, a thing good.</head>
            <p>TAke nine or fifteen leaves of small laurel, dry them and make into powder, and mix it with honeyed water, and so give it to your beast in the morning fasting: Or, you may take the green leafs of the said plant, nine or fifteen of them; stamp them with a pint of honeyed wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a little salt; strain out the juice, and give it to your beast in the morning fasting: this purgeth strongly. Also madder (which Diers use) steeped in milk, and given as beforesaid, purgeth very well, and very safe. Also the leafs
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:206326:48"/>of the alder bruised and boiled in water, then strained and the water given, doth purge both choler and flegm downward, and cleanseth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of the stomack of either man or beast. Also the berries of the same tree, stampt with Ale or Beer, doth the like. Or the inner bark, while it is green, stampt with wine, and so let it stand all night cold, being close from the air, and then strain it in the morning; make it blood warm, and give it to your beast. The greater quantity you give of any of these medicines, the stronger they will be to work. Therefore be wise in their use, and when you cause your catcle to purge, keep them warm a night or two; forget not this at your peril.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To stop fluxes, time best.</head>
               <p>THE best purging is, when the moon is in <hi>Scorpio</hi> or <hi>Pisces:</hi> and the best time to stop fluxes or laxes is, when the moon is in <hi>Taurus, Virgo,</hi> or <hi>Capricorn;</hi> then to give your beasts drink to stop fluxes, is the best time. <hi>Probatum est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Collick-cattle to help.</head>
               <p>GIve to your Oxe, or other beast, garlick piled, and beaten small, and so mixt with white wine, or strong Beer, while it is yet new, or working in the fat, and so given is very good, or bruised leeks in the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; but be sure to give it three or four mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings fasting, and it will not fail.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:206326:48"/>
            <head>Gurling or rumbling in the belly.</head>
            <p>WHen your beast, oxe, or cow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath a rumbling in the belly, and noise in his guts, you shall see him lie down often, and rise up again suddenly, because he cannot rest for pain; also you may hear a noise of wind in his belly. To help this grievance, ye shall give him onions, beaten small and boiled in sweet wine: Or give him of fenelseed, aniseed, and cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minseed, of each half an ounce, beaten very small, and boiled in sweet sack, or very strong ale: also let him blood under the tail, and so he will recover. Proved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Shrew run to help, nature of that mouse.</head>
            <p>THE shrew is a small mouse, with a very long nose, she is more black than another mouse. If you know her not from other mice, you may obserne the cat; for when she doth catch one of these mice, she doth play with it, and kill it, but eats it not.</p>
            <p>Her nature is such, that if she run over any limb of man or beast, they suddenly fall lame, as though they were benum'd; and if it run o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the back or loins of a beast, then he cannot rise behind, no nor stand when he is helpt up, but go on his knees, and draw his hinder part after him, yet eat and drink if it be given him. This I have seen and helpt, but herein be not deceived; for a beast that hath his back bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the great marrow-bones of his thighs bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or the buckle-bones out of their cups, have the same signs, as I have often seen: but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:206326:49"/>then you may know by feeling those bones, and if they be broken, you may hear them rattle, when he is set on his feet; but if his bones and sinews be sound, yet lame as is abovesaid, then you may safely conclude, that he is shrew-run.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is;</head>
               <p>Tak some boughs or twigs of a shrew-tree, and beat and rub the lame limb, or lame back of the beast, make it smart with beating, and hot with rubbing; Do it two or three dayes, twice a day, and it helpeth; this I have proved true: or, you may carry the beast to a briar that grows at both the ends, and draw him through the boughs thereof under the briar twice or thrice, alwayes the same way. This is said to help, but I have not proved it. If your beast be run over the heart, he will be sick as well as lame in his farther parts; and to remedy this, ye shall cause the beast to eat some tender twigs of the shrew tree, by putting them into his grinders, or jaw-teeth, and to beat and rub his body. Also proved.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>How to make the said shrew-tree.</head>
                  <p>TAke a shrew-mouse alive, hold her by the tail, that she lame not your hand: then let one bore a hole in a tree with an auger; make it three or four inches deep, if the tree be a big one: then put in the mouse, and drive a pin af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her to keep her in, yet so, as not to kill her, but let her dye there by famine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The tree being thus made, when you have occasion to use it, as before is taught, then
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:206326:49"/>break or cut so many of the branches as you will use at once, but let them not touch the earth, till the work you intend be done. The tree or trees you are to make use of are, either oak, ash, elm, or withy-sallie; all proved.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Tetter on cattle to help.</head>
            <p>THis is an unseemly scab or scurviness, yet doth little hurt to the beast, for it groweth but on the outward part of his body, and is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove six moneths before it fall away of it self: some are broad, and some grow long, and hang like clusters of grapes, with many kernels and knobs, somewhat hard, and of a hory colour, and a little inclining to blue.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The remedy is;</head>
               <p>Ye shall mix ointment with tar, and a little gray sope, of all a like quantity, and heat it, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n anoint those teters therewith, so often as you see cause, and this will heal it: some sear them with a hot iron, and then anoint them with tar onely; both proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A medicine for all kind of griefs in cattle.</head>
            <p>TAke two penyworth of treacle, a handful of hempseed, a portion of juy-leafs, and el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or box-tree leaves, of fetherfew as much as a tennis ball, of clay of a wall that hath no lime in it, and so much of bay-salt; put thereto of urine, and a little soot of a chimney; then stir all these well together, and make it warm, and so give it to each beast three good spoonfulls thereof: and lastly, before they go from you ye shall give to each beast a little tar, or give
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:206326:50"/>them in drink the dryed flowers of wormwood mixt with some salt. Thus ye may use your sheep and other cattle against all diseases: it asswageth most pains in cattle, or hurtful diseases in them, either in head or body.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Blood-pissing by a strain, or tallow melted by hasty driving of a beast.</head>
            <p>IF an oxe fat be melted, he falls away sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and his dung is black, greasse, and stinking; if he be strained, he doth piss and dung blood, and is quickly weak.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The remedy is;</head>
               <p>Ye shall give him four ounces of the cruds of runit in a pint of milk; do this so soon as you espy his grievance: Then keep him from water twenty and four hours, and then give him eight ounces of the foresaid cruds in a quart of sweet milk, and let him not drink of four hours after; yet give him either grass, or green athtree leafs to eat.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Pontasie in a beast so help.</head>
            <p>IF any beast have this disease, he will shake much, and quiver in his flanks, and pant.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is;</head>
               <p>You shall give him a litcle runner, soot, and urine mixt together; give it three or four mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings together, and it helpeth. But in this case be careful, lest the signs deceive you; and the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease prove a feaver, either common or pestilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:206326:50"/>
            <head>Blood in the backs of cattle.</head>
            <p>IF your cattle be troubled with blood in their backs (as sometimes beasts are) then they will go as though they drew their heads aside, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The remedy is;</head>
               <p>To let the beast blood in the vein, under his tail, and let him bleed well: Then stop the blood either with bruised nettles and salt, or with part of a dust ball, as is taught before, and he will do well.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Bulls their diseases, or hurts.</head>
            <p>BUlls have no diseases; but what are common to other beasts, except in their members of generation; and in these hurts, our old Authors are silent; yet in my practice, I was twice called to cure such hurts. The first was a young bull, whose yard hung out, and was covered all over with mire and dirt, which was dry, and hard ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thereon.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure was this;</head>
               <p>First, I washt it with strong beer and butter, boiled together, and made it clean; then I see it was raw and sore; and for the remedy, I drest it twice a day with swines grease and goose grease mixt together, and within four dayes he drew it up into the sheath, amended, and served cows well as before; but how this hurt came was not known.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The second Bulls cure.</head>
               <p>This was a great strong town-bull of three years old, his yard hung out, was very stiff and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:206326:51"/>hard, and exceeding hot and sore, with many scabs thereon; it was thought he took his hurt by serving many kine, it being in the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> the chief time for cows in <hi>Cheshire.</hi> But some judged the cause to be one cow, that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued proud two or three dayes. The cure I used was; First, I washed it very well with the juice of chickweed and plantine, and got off the scabs, so that it was raw and did bleed; then I anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with swines grease, as the former, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any better at that time. This was done twice a day, though I lived far remote, and within four dayes he drew up his yard, yet was two moneths before he was perfectly well. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son was the hot weather, serving many kine, and the means used were not so good, as I found since.</p>
               <p>If thou be called to any the like cure, then take this course following. First, wash the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber very well with this water following;</p>
               <p>Take a quart of Smiths water, that which they cool their hot iron in, one handful of sage, and a good quantity of alome, and three spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of honey; boyl all these together, till half a pint be wasted; then strain and wring out the sage, and keep the water in a cup or glass close stopt. Then take a good quantity of clean linen rags, and burn them to fine ashes, and when you have washed the sore member with the water, then strew it all over with these ashes, and wrap it with a soft and clean flaxen cloath, and tye an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other course cloath under his belly, and over his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:206326:51"/>back, to hold the other fast for falling away. Do this twine a day, and in a short time he will be well, but keep him in the house from cows, if it be possible. And for a hurt like the first, use the same cure there prescribed. Once I saw a young bull that was strained, and pissed blood, but he dyed the same day, before any help was used; and when he was opened, his bladder was full of blood. In this case I know no other cure, but that for blood-pissing in. If a bulls stones be crusht and broken, the onely cure is to gold him: the manner how to do it I need not teach, its so well known. The like way is to be taken with a horse in such a case.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Diseases and hurts of kine; and first, if she cannot calve, to help her.</head>
            <p>IF you see your cow long in labour, and strain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to calve, yet is not able to bring forth, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther because the passage is too small; or else, that the calf doth not lie right for the birth: in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of these cases, you are to help her your self, or procure some one that hath skill to do it. The manner how is this, your cow being laid down on her left side (as alwayes they do in this case) make your arm bare, and wet all your arm and hand in warm water; then set your four fingers ends and thumb close together, and so put it up into her body, and feel if the calf lie right for the birth, which is, if the nose lie towards you, and both the fore-feet; if so, then draw the two feet both together, so far, till you may see them; then put up your hand again, and take the calf
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:206326:52"/>by the lower chap, or put your fingers between the jaw-bones under his chin, and if you can put up the other hand to his nose, so holding his neck straight, draw it towards you, till its nose be as forward as its feet; then take the feet in your right hand, and the ears in your left hand, and draw it forth. But in all this work, you had best lie on your belly, and lean on your elbows, it is the best and easiest way. Now if the calf lie right, and yet the passage be so narrow, that you cannot draw it forth, as is taught; then take a small cord, and make a running neuse or loop on the end thereof, make it to run very easily, put the loop on your fingers ends, so that you may put it off with your thumb, upon the calfs chap, or over his head, as your need is; then let one or two draw gently at the cord, and your self to guide the calfs head and feet with both your hands, till you have it; if the passage be not so straight, that it cannot be got by this means, if so, then there is no other nor better way to save the cow alive, than to cut the calfs head in pieces with the stump of a knife, which hath no more of the blade than a man may hide in his hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the haft. Also for this work he must have an iron hook, with an eye at the one end, to tye a cord to, and the point of the hook sharp, to enter the skin of the calf; so he may set the hook on the lower chap of the calf, or what part else he intends to cut, and let one draw gently at the cord and hook, whilest he cuts that part away whereon the hook is fastned, and so to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:206326:52"/>part, till he have it all. Then give your cow a quart of strong beer, and an ounce of aniseeds beaten to small powder, and mixt with the beer, to which add one handful of mallows, or mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort leafs, beaten small to comfort her, and cause her to cast her later birth; and if she were not crusht before you took this course, she will mend and do well; often proved.</p>
            <p>Now if the calf come not the right way, but the shoulder forward, and the head bowed back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the hip (as oft they do) then set the ball of your hand to its shoulder, and put it up into the cows belly from the birth: then put up your hand to its head, and bring the head down and the foremost feet, and so reduce it to a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral birth, and then draw it as is taught.</p>
            <p>But if the rump come first (as sometimes it doth) put it up as you did the shoulder, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it to a natural birth if you can, if not, then keep it up from the birth, till you can get forth the two hinder feet: then let some one draw at them, and do you guide the rump with your hands, till you deliver the cow of her burden. This with discretion you must work, and which way soever the calf lies, reduce it to a natural birth, if it be possible; if not, you are well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed by these two examples. But if you must needs draw a calf, be sure to draw downwards, fromwards the cows back, and draw hatd, as need requires, but not rashly; so you shall have your desire, and the cow do well. <hi>Probatum est.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:206326:53"/>
               <head>Note this cure as followeth;</head>
               <p>Once I was called to a cow, that could not calve in the year 1667, she had lien two dayes, was very big at the birth-place, but no room for the calf to come forth, for the mouth of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix was so strait, that I had much pain to force up my middle finger, yet she strain'd with all her strength; so that if it had been possible to break way on the one side the natural passage: here the cause was desperate, and so the cure must be also; yet all did well, with much care and labour of her Keeper, after the first work was done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cure.</head>
               <p>For the effecting this work, I got a very sharp knife, the blade not above two inches long, held it so between my fingers (they being held straight, yet close together, that I carryed it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the neck of the Mother, till I came to the narrow mouth thereof, not hurting the passage at all: Then guiding the knife with my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger, and holding the haft with my other fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and thumb, I cut open the mouth of the Matrix, till I had room sufficient to draw away the Calve: which was then quickly done, and she cast her later birth the same day; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three weeks got strength to rise her self, and became a good Beif within the year. The Calve had milk of an other Cow, and is now a good Cow, 1670. This cure did well, but I think the better way had been to have cut open her side in the flank on the milking side, and to have
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:206326:53"/>taken forth the Calve that way, and sown up the wound as was taught before for a Cow or other beast that was goared, or panched. This is for thy example if need require.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To help a Cow of the whetherd, that is, when she hath Calved and cannot Clean.</head>
               <p>VVHetherd, that is, when a Cow hath new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Calved, and hath not cast her Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as many do (and many dye thereof.)</p>
               <p>To make her cast and avoid the same, ye shall take a good quantity of the juice of Mallowes, and mix it with Ale and give it to her with a horn, it is well proved. Also the juice of mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, given in the same manner is good to clense her, and also to bring forth a dead Calve. Also smoaked Barley given her to eat, and luke-warm water to drink, all very good and often proved.</p>
               <p>To get the juice of your herbs tis best to beat them small in a morter or dish, mix them with your Ale or Beer, wring or strain out the herbs, and so give it to your Cow blood-warm, often proved. Yet when all these fail (as some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they do.) Then some use to put up their hand, it being first anointed with soft grease, and loose the cleaning from amongst the rough knots, and burs of the mother, unto knots or burs it sticks fast: and pull it away by pieces, then put in a good lump of butter, and so let him go, and she will do well. But if the matrix be much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, yea, very hot and sore, then your best course is to take a good quantity of the juice of plantine, of Chick-weed, knot grass, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:206326:54"/>hous'-green, or any two of them, beat them small, strain out the juice, and mix it with hogs grease that is not salted, &amp; boil it till the grease be all melted, then let it cool, and with your hand put it into the mother as far as you can: this doth both cool and comfort it very much. Do this two or three dayes, and she will do well: Thou mayest know she mends, if she eat and cease to strain: if she do not leave straining, but avoid stinking brownish matter out of the matrix, there is little hope of life. If this accident hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in winter, when there is not herbs (as oft it doth) then take two ounces of <hi>mel rosarum,</hi> and half a pint of strong beer, and mix them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and being blood-warm, put it into a glister bladder, and with the pipe spurt it into the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Do this three dayes, and she will be well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Descension, or falling out of the matrix.</head>
               <p>IT happeneth many times, that a cow with straining to clean (after she hath calved) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth down the mother, then there is great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death, if present help be not found, yea, many do dye thereof in the winters nights, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be espyed, it being perished with cold.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The cure.</head>
                  <p>When the womb of a cow is faln out, your first work is, to lay a sheet or great cloath under it as she lieth, or to hold under it, if she stand; then take all the cleaning clean off the mother, but do not take off the burs or knots that stick fast to she ends of the veins thereof, for fear she bleed to death, as I have seen, otherwise those
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:206326:54"/>knots must and will come off, before the womb be clean; but it is better to let them rot away, (as they will in time) than run the hazard of her bleeding, which is so hard to stay. The clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being clean taken away, take a quart of strong beer, wherein boil four ounces of salt butter, and as hot as you can abide your hands in it, wash the mother therewith, and make it clean. This done, put it up with both your hands, till it be within her body: then having your arm bare to the shoulder, put the matrix into its right place, and be sure that it be all turned, and lie not on lumps; if you do it right, one may feel your hand by laying his hand on the cows belly, before her udder is on the outside: then draw back your hand softly, that you may leave the mother behind you; then put two or three lumps of salt butter into the mother, as far as you can, and be sure you leave her in the right place. Then stitch it up in this manner, to keep in the mother, in case it offer to descend again; Take two little shreads of shoe-leather, of two inches and a half long, and half an inch broad; bure two holes in each of them one inch and a half a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder; then with a great flat-pointed needle, and a strong double thread, as big as a shoe-thread; stitch those two pieces of leather on each side the cows shape, and tie it together, not too close, but that she may make water, and let it remain till she be well, which will be in few dayes; often proved. Note, That the two pieces of leather are to keep the shape from cutting
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:206326:55"/>with the thread, and to hold it straight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But Reader, in all this I have taught thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning these accidents happening to kine, I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose thee to have an acute and ready wit, and a nimble and active hand, else not to undertake any of these magnetick works, that require so much agility both of head and hand. But for an help in all these, and any of this kind, I advise thee th repair to some slaughter-man or Butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and see him open his slaughtered beeves, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia ly cows; yea, such as have calves in their bellies: mark well how they lie in the matrix, how it grows, and all the parts thereof. Also the guts and their parts, the veins and sinews where, where they lie, and to what use they serve. Use this often in thy practice, for hereby thou maist become excellent in art.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w new calved, sick by drinking cold water, how to help.</head>
            <p>A Cow may be sick with drinking much cold water when she hath new calved, and then she must be helped, by giving her hot spices and st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong beer.</p>
            <p>Once I was called to medicine a cow in this case, she calved in <hi>May,</hi> in very hot weather; she being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery fat, was hot and dry, and drunk much cold water at a brook, near the place where she calved; by this means her belly swell'd, and she did eat nothing all that day, but lay all along on the earth, with her legs stretcht out, and was thought to be incurable. Now when I saw in what case she was, and heard by what means she
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:206326:55"/>came to it: then I concluded her stomack and inward parts to be stupified with the cold water, and that the remedy must be hot and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and so it was; for I gave her long pepper, two penyworth, grains one penyworth, and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seed one ounce, all beaten to fine powder, and mixt with two quarts of strong ale, and half a pint of aqua-vitae, and one penyworth of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and gave it at twice, one hour between the the times; the last was after Sun-setting, and within two hours after, we put her legs close to her body by force, turned her on her belly, and with a little holding she sat up, and held up her head, though weakly, and about midnight, she did eat ivy leafs, being put between her grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and so recovered, and did well.</p>
            <p>But all this while the Butcher was kept there to have dressed her for meat, if I had but said that I doubted of her life. By this example work in the like case, but with discretion, making your medicines stronger or weaker, as you see need.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>White wast in a Cow to help.</head>
            <p>THE white wast in a cow doth weaken her ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much, and in time will kill her, if remedy be not found: it comes by some strain in the small of her back and loins, whereby the sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick vessels are so weakened, that they cannot hold and retain the seed, but it falleth down into the womb, there putrifies, and so passeth from her in a white yellowish water, much like to the stinking gunary of a man: all cows haue such like matter pass from them, soon after their calving,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:206326:56"/>till the yard throughly cleansed, but not after, it free from this infirmity; neither is that which runneth from the reins so thick and well conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as this, but thin and raw, and continues long after her calving, and weakens the beast, as is before said; and by these signs ye may know it from her natural cleansing.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is;</head>
               <p>Take one dram of the fine powder of cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and boil it in a quart of farrow-cows milk, and give it to her with a horn, in the morning fasting, being blood-warm; let her fast two hours after. Do this nine mornings together, and it helpeth; <hi>probatum est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Ʋdder of a cow hurt or inflamed.</head>
            <p>IF the udder or teats of a cow be cut, goared, staked, bitten or torn with a dog, in all these the cure is one and the same.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The cure is;</head>
               <p>Take of the glear fat of bacon, and with the fire tongs made red hot, or any other hot iron, fry out the fat: then to two ounces of that burnt fat, add one ounce of common turpentine, and as much tar; work them to a perfect salve, and if the udder be torn, cut away the loose pieces and jags that hang down, and make the sore even and handsom: then anoint it twice a day with the foresaid salue, and it helps. Proved.</p>
               <p>But if he be goared with a beasts horn, or sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:206326:56"/>then you must take clean linen rags, and make tents of them; roll your tents in the salve, and put them into the wounds, also tie some cloath under her belly, and over her back, to keep in the tents. Do this twice a day, till she be whole.</p>
               <p>But if her udder be crusht or inflamed, and swell, and be very hot, then your cure is first to scarifie it lightly, yet in many places, and lose out the chafed and scalded blood: then, if it be in summer, (as commonly it is) take a good quantity of chickweed, and as much clevers, and the like much of knotgrass; beat them small, and boil them in vineger, or strong sowre beer a good quantity, thicken it with wheat-bran, and make a great pultas; spread it on a cloath, and lay it to the sore udder blood-warm, and assoon as it is dry, renew it. But if it be in winter, when herbs cannot be got, then take Album graecum, a dogs white turd, and mix it with your vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; make it thick like pap, spread it on a cloath, and lay it on the sore udder, and when it is dry, renew it. But if it do Imposthumate, and come to ripeness, then lance it in the softest place, thrust out the quitter, and tent it with the salve as is taught before twice a day till it be well.</p>
               <p>Now in <hi>England,</hi> they use to rub a cows udder that is hard or swoln, with the fine earth that a mole hath new cast up, and many do mend
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:206326:57"/>thereby. AlSo if you take a quick mole, and rub and roll her between your hands till she dye, she giveth such a magnetick vertue to your hands, that if you rub and stroak a cows udder that is hard and whetston'd with them, it doth amend in short time. Or, if she give blood with her milk, do stroak her paps, and draw out the blood two or three dayes, and it helps; <hi>probatum est.</hi> Yea, though thou kill but one mole, as is said in all your life, yet your hands retain the vertue for ever after; this I have often proved.</p>
               <p>If your cows paps be clapt with intemperate cold, and heat of the air, or scratcht with briars, or any the like sorance, then your cure is; Take dock-roots that are firm and sound, wash and scrape them clean; then beat them very small, and boil them in fresh butter, and when they are well boiled, strain out the butter into a cup o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dish, and it will be a fine yellow salve, with which salve, let your maids anoint and stroak the cows teats, when she hath done milking, and in so doing three or four dayes, twice a day, they will be whole. Often proved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Milk wanting in a cow new calved.</head>
            <p>IF your new-calved cow want milk, either through poverty, sickness, want of meat, or that she is naturally a dry bag; if the defect be by poverty, and that poverty be for want of meat, then I hope you know your cure, which is only supply the want.</p>
            <p>If the poverty come by sickness, then remove the cause by convenient medicine, and the effect
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:206326:57"/>ceaseth. If her dryness be natural, it is hard to remedy; yet in all these cases, those things are found most excellent helps.</p>
            <p>Take aniseeds one ounce, fenel-seeds as much, beat them to fine powder, and boil them in a quart of good ale or beer, and give it her luke-warm. Also boil the leafs of coleworts in water, and give it her to drink, or give her the leafs raw to eat. Or, if she be very poor, give her two quarts of boiled barley to eat every day, and the water it was boiled in to drink; boil fenel seeds therein, or fenel it self: boil your barley till it break, boil it in a good quantity of water to serve your cow most of the day. Use this three week less or more, as you see need; it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent help, yea, the best I ever found.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Biting of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad Dog, or other venemous beasts.</head>
            <p>THE biting of a mad dog, or any other mad beast, venemous beast, or stinging with ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents is poysonous, and destroyes the body and lise of man and beast, in one kind or other, as all poysons do, if taken and not soon remedied. But my intended task at this time, is onely to shew the signs, and teach the cure for the biting of a mad dog, or any other mad beast; as wolf, fox, cat, or swine being mad, by the poyson of a mad dog. These being all poysonous, and many more; some poysonous, and some venemous, causeth me to speak a little of poysonous sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, the better to inform my Readers, I mean the vulgar sort, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:206326:58"/>
            <head>Venom or poyson is of three sorts;</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. Some living creatures are poysonous:</item>
               <item>2. Some herbs and plants are poysonous.</item>
               <item>3. Some minerals and metals are poysonous.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And as the venoms and poysons are many, so they have sundry wayes of workings, yet all to the destruction of man, and all humane nature. For, whether nature be the matter, form, or whole frame of man. These poysons corrupt all the materials of the body of man or beast, both the humours, the spirits, and the solid parts; and that these may be corrupted by poyson, no man doubteth; yet some may perhaps say, How comes it to pass that some are not hurt by poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons? To this I answer; That some men have such a strong constitution of Nature, that hardly any poyson inwardly taken, (unless it be a great quantity) will hurt them, neither the biting of venemous beasts so soon as others; and some are so subject to vomit, that they cast up poyson be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can corrode or operate.</p>
            <p>Now, of living creatures that are poysonous, and of the divers and sundry workings of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, of so many as I have seen or read of:</p>
            <p>First, The Dragon kills by his sting, though he bite not, nor suck the blood.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Crocodile is poyson, as some say: others say, his flesh is very good meat. However, if he catch either man or beast, he is sure to eat that.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The touch of the Viper causeth the body to swell, and dye suddenly.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:206326:58"/>
            <p>Fourthly, The poyson of the Asp causeth sleep, and the head to swell.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The biting of Hemorrhous draweth the blood from all parts of the body.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Dipsas with his double head, makes thirsty, and so kills.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The Newt poysoneth the water.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, The bite of the Prester, causeth the mouth of the wounded to foam, and gape wide.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, The Seps his biting consumes the bones, and dissolves the body.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, The Basilisk is said to kill by fight onely (and that I believe, as I do the story of the Phoenix, the Salamander, the Fly perausta, and slow boots) These are a fearful brood, yet stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in these our temperate Islands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Venemous Creatures in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>First, Of the Adder; If this Ell-like creature sting any man, the part becometh of a leady co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; and if it be not remedied with speed, the poyson ascends to the heart, and the wounded member rots; and if good help be not found, loss of life or limb ensues.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Slow worm, or Blind worm, it is very venemous, the stingings of it are very small, and scarce appear to the eye; the wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed part is red, and the whole body becometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed; and if present help he not found, death is at hand.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of the Toad, it is a most venemous creature, and poysoneth the part of the body she
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:206326:59"/>toucheth, maketh it inflame, swell, and to stand on dew-drops: Of all poysons it is the sweetest in the mouth, and thee most deadly; for it kills in less than three hour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, being either eaten or drunken.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There are Askers which are very poysonous, they are of two kinds, one living on the land, and the other in the water. Also there are Effs in the hot Chiltern Countrey, which are venemous; of these I onely heard, but see them not. And there are snakes, which are small lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle creatures, with four feet, very like to an Ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but very swift in running; but I know no hurt in them; there are many of them in this land, they keep commonly in the bogs.</p>
            <p>Also there are Hornits, Wasps, Bees, and Ants, whose stingings are not very hurtful, yet vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, if they bite or sting. And the Spider, and Connought worm poysonous, and yet S. <hi>Patrick</hi> left them behind when he drove the venemous creatures out of this land.</p>
            <p>Poysonous Plants and Herbs, of which there are many that poyson and destroy the body of man; some by inflaming and blistering the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts being eaten, or the juice of them drunk. Some causing the eyes to start out; also causing raving and death; and some causing death by sleeping. And the like may be said of Minerals, (but I forbear to describe them, for fear the envious should make use of them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish their mischievous desires.) But the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:206326:59"/>poyson of the mad dog is contrary to all other poysons, as I shall make it appear.</p>
            <p>Of all the poysons that I have read of, there is none that work upon the rational senses, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wolfs bane, and that I judge to be, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive pain it causeth. The poyson of Asps and Opium kill by sleep, they so stupifie the sensitive parts. But the poyson of the Dog doth so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy both the rational and sensitive parts, that they grow so mad, as that they regard nothing but to fight, bite, scratch, and destroy any they can, neither regarding friend or foe, neither doth man or beast either eat or sleep, when he is mad by this kind of poyson, neither take any rest till he be cured by death; and few escape, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they get help in time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Signs to know a mad Dog by.</head>
            <p>If the dog be your own, and you observe him bite and snap his fellows, and not play at all, neither grin nor snarl much when he biteth; or if he bite or snap you, or your people, or Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, not being urged thereto; neither was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to do so before: and eat little, and sleep not, but is in continual motion; yet barks not at strangers as before, but snaps them, all these are suspicious signs.</p>
            <p>Also if you see a strange dog run about gape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and driveling at the mouth, holding down his tail alwayes, and hanging out his tongue also if he hurt not, nor take notice where other dogs have file, or use to piss, and do the like there; or if he snatch and bite any thing and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:206326:60"/>do not bark, or if other dogs shun him, or stand a loof and bark at him, all these are signs that he is mad.</p>
            <p>The cause of dogs going mad is black choller, or, melancholy adust, which getting the mastery in their bodies, through vehement heat over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the senses, and makes him mad; for the strength of this burnt choler infecteth his brain, and so from thence to the tongue and teeth, and maketh them venemous. Therefore if either man or beast be bitten with such a mad dog, he is in danger to go mad also. But of this I need not speak, it is so well known. And as the biting is perillous, so is the slaver also, and may causg madness without biting. This slaver is easily tae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken, as by a mad dogs touching ones lips with his mouth, or one dog another, and so of othe-creatures; for the skin of the lips of man or beast is tender, more soft and spungious than or ther parts, and very apt to take this kind o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyson.</p>
            <p>Also if the slayer of a mad dog fall in water, it infecteth the same; or on grass, it infecteth it. And if any beast drink of the infected water, or eat of the grass before it be cleansed, they are in danger to go mad; and if one of these mad beasts bite either man or beast, they are in the like danger.</p>
            <p>Whatsoever is bitten by a mad dog, or recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his slaver, is in danger to go mad, though some sooner, and some later, according to the constitution of their bodies, the vehemency of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:206326:60"/>the venome, and the quantity received. In some it lies hid a year, in some two or three moneths, and in some two or three dayes: yea, I was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly told of one, that took this poyson onely by the touch of the lips, and fell stark mad the same night; yea, bit his wife in bed, and she went mad, and both dyed in three dayes time.</p>
            <p>The man that told me this, was one that came to me for the medicine to help one that was bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a mad dog. He said, There was a young man, and his wife, going to visit her father and mother, met a mad dog, which assalted a grey-hound they had; the man having no weapon but a pocket knife, as this man said, pull'd it out, and stab'd the mad dog, and kill'd him; put up his knife, not heeding to make it clean; but being set at his supper, saw his knife soul with blood, and slaver of the dog, he wet it in his mouth, and dried it on his shirt, after his supper, went to bed, had a sleep, but wakened mad, bit his wife, who told of his killing the dog, after he had bitten her, and before she was mad. If this were true, as he solemnly protested it was, it was a lamentable case: but the truth is, there were many people and cattle bitten, and dyed in the years 1658, 1659, and 1660, in which years a multitude of dogs ran mad, also wolves and foxes, and many foxes were killed by cowherds and others, not being able to make any escape for madness. One mad fox came to my house in the day-time, but not known to be mad, was killed by my dogs; he bit a maistiff, and a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitch,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:206326:61"/>and they both run mad, not being medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cined, because we did not think the fox to be mad. Also there came a mad wolf-bitch into the Town of <hi>Lemonahan,</hi> in the <hi>Kings County,</hi> and Barony of <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i-castle,</hi> in the day-time, and bit hogs and sheep, and one cow, and they all dyed for want of help. Also the said wolf bit one young maid, about Eight or Nine years old, pull'd the top of her head bare, so that the bone was uncovered a hands breadth or more. Also he set upon a man that came to save the child, bit him by the arm, by the nose and lips; he caught the wolf in his arms, cried out for help, fell down with the wolf, yet held her fast, and one of his Neighbours knockt the wolf in the head with an axe, and so ended the quarrel. This man and the child came both to me for physick, had the medicine twice, got salve for the wounds, and both recovered, and did well.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Signs of going mad in them that are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a mad dog.</head>
               <p>IF man, woman, or child be bitten with a mad dog, and begin to go mad, you may know by these signs following:</p>
               <p>First, they begin to wake much, and cannot sleep nor rest, but are disquiet in mind, and compliance of it, yet know not the cause: if they get any sleep, it is accompanied with fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful dreams; they sigh, and are angry without cause, and some in this case do bark like dogs, and are ashamed to be seen of others, and are in fear of water, and regard not whether they eat
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:206326:61"/>or drink, or not: their eyes are fiery red, and they have a fiery countenance. All these, or any of them are doubtful signs, and ye had need to make hast with the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re; but if any one be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a dog, he or she may know if the dog be mad at the first, and get help with speed, and not stay for these fearful signs. How to know the dog is mad, I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>each in the next Page.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Signs of a beast bitten with a mad dog, and begin to go mad.</head>
               <p>A beast being bitten with a mad dog, or that hath lickt up his slaver with his grass, or drunk it with his water (for all is one) doth first begin to bellow softly, as though he were merry; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, scrape and set his head aside at his fellows, as though he would play with them: his eyes are red, and stare wide open, and he looks furiously; soon after he grows more wild, roars aloud, scrapes on ditch-banks, and roots them with his nose, and prokes them with his horns, fights with his fellows, leaves his merry beginning, and lows amain, and doth neither eat, drink, nor sleep, but low continually, and in few days dyes. And what is here said of a beast, bull, oxe, or cow, the like signs are found in a horse; for, he begins with play in his manner, and after falls to fighting, biting, pawing, running and ramping, and neither eat nor sleep till he dye: and as the vulgar say, a beast, oxe, or cow hath the lowing Evil when mad: So they say, a horse hath the mad staggers, when in this case. Also swine do the like, begin with mirth, and end with mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:206326:62"/>But these are the worst to cure; therefore if you know they are bitten, make hast with their cure; for, if you stay for these signs, it is too late, and one mad swine will poyson a whole herd in a day, and they will all go mad, if reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be not found with speed. Sheep will go mad also, if bitten by a mad dog, or mad hog; but they are the most mild of all creatures in this case, and swine the most dangerous, for they cease not biting, whatever they come near, if once mad. Truly I saw once in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of swine, wherein four were mad; and when we had got the whole herd into a house, no man durst venture in to separate the sound from the sick, they were so fierce. Also cats, geese, ducks, and hens will go mad, if bitten with a mad dog. Note also, that whether man or beast becometh mad this way, and biteth any other creature, it will go mad also: and that poultry will go mad, I have seen it my self. And Dr. <hi>Read</hi> in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of wounds, tells me, That <hi>Boctius in Tracta venen.</hi> writeth, that he saw a man kill'd by a mad house cock.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Signs that the dog is mad.</head>
               <p>If your own dog bite you, or any of your own people, or do snap your cattle, be sure he is mad, except you tread on him, or otherwayes hurt him; or, that he be a wrangling cur, and use to bite and snatch, as some do. But if you see a strange dog bite, or snatch your cattle, or bite your self, he being from home, and have not hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> master, or some of his garments; or some of his
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:206326:62"/>people to tend, and you approach too near him; if none of these be, be sure he is mad, and you had best seek for remedy with speed.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Now of the cure.</head>
                  <p>Those that have written of this malady, have prescribed many remedies, both for the healing of the wound, and to preserve from madness; and for the first, their cure will do well, for any salve that will help the biting of a sound dog, will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so cure the biting of a mad dog But for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, remedies to preserve from going mad, they prove clouds without rain, for the most part. This is well known to the whole Countrey, who see men remediless in this case, and dye miserably, when they have wasted their coyn in seeking remedy at Doctors, and their friends wait for their recovery, till they wish to have them dye out of their misery. For this cause I have not inserted any of their remedies in this Treatise, but onely that which I bought dear, and have found true; yea, it did not fail me these thirty years, being taken in time; but the sooner it is taken after the biting, the better, experience teacheth this.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The cure for man or beast.</head>
                  <p>When man, woman, or child is bitten with a mad dog, wolf, or fox, or any other mad beast, the liver of the same dog or beast being taken and roasted, and so eaten by the party that is bitten, is a present remedy; often proved. It is also as good for dogs, or any other beast that is bitten with a mad dog; but if the liver cannot
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:206326:63"/>be gotten, as seldom it can; then this following medicine hath not a second.</p>
                  <p>Take of To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mentil roots clean washt &amp; scrap't two ounces, beat them very small in a morter or dish, then put them into a quart of strong new beer or ale, and work them well together by stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; then strain out the beer through a coarse linen cloath, into a cup or dish; then put to the said beer so strained, one dram of Castorium, and as much Assasetida, and one scruple of Lignum Aloes, all made into fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e powder. Mix the ale and these very well together, and let the patient drink one half at night, going to bed, and the other half in the morning, and fast two hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; this dose is for strong people. But for them that are weak, or children, give half so much or less at a time. Give according to the age and strength of your patient; if the tast do offend the patient, sweeten it with sugar or aniseeds; but if they have been long neglected, and begin to be mad, then let them blood in the common vein, and take a good quantity of the blood, if they be strong, and give a bigger dose of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, and more times, as you see need. If they refuse to take the medicine (as sure they will) then hold them fast, and with a splent made for that purpose, open their mouths, and pour in the medicine with a spoon, or other convenient instrument, but take heed, lest they bite you, for if they do, you are in much danger, and must take a medicine your self, or go mad; yea, soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than if you were bitten with a dog.</p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:206326:63"/>
                  <p>Take care of weak and old folks, and young children in letting of blood, and take but little, for fear of a sincop, and death come in the place of a cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The cure for swine and dogs.</head>
                  <p>If either swine or dog be bitten with a mad dog, or any other mad beast, give the same quantity of the medicine as is taught before, with sweet milk; if they will not eat it, then pour it into their mouths, but beware of biting; and if they begin to be mad before you begin your cure, its better to kill them, than to trouble and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger your self with them.</p>
                  <p>If any hound, grey-hound, setting-dog, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, or spaniel, which is much worth in his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters esteem, be bitten, and begin to go mad, and refuse to eat, then hold him fast, so that he bite not, and open his mouth with a staff, and pour in a pint or more of the medicine made very strong, and keep him safe tied in a dark place: give it three or four times, as at night and morning, two dayes together; if he do once begin to eat, then it is sure he recovers, and so of all other beasts.</p>
                  <p>For the cure of great beasts and horses, take this example following; but for a horse, put one penyworth of treacle into your medicine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The cure of a young oxe or bullock, that began to be mad.</head>
                  <p>In <hi>August</hi> 1663, I had a young oxe began to be mad, being bitten, as I thought, but how long before I know not, neither found any hurt on his body; however, the signs of being mad
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:206326:64"/>by the biting of a mad dog, were evidence enough that it was so; for he began to roar, and scrape on the earth, run at ditch-banks, fight with his fellows, and would neither eat nor drink. He was first heard to roar gently on Saturday night at Nine a clock, but I supposed it to be a bullock that was in the company, and used to bellow on that wise, therefore took the less heed, and did not look them till the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but on Sunday morning, I found him as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovesaid, got help, and brought him home, let him blood in the neck-vein, and took a great quantity. Then I gave him four ounces of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentil-roots made clean and beaten, as is before taught, and one dram of castorium, and as much assafetida, and one scruple of lignum aloes, all beaten small, as before is taught, and very well mixt with three pints of strong beer, and so kept him fast tied in the house where he scraped with his feet, brake the wall with his horns, and was unquiet that day. Then at night I gave him half a pint of hempseed beaten small, and mixt with three pints of strong beer to make him sleep. The next morning, I gave him the first medicine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; soon after he began to eat, at night I put him forth, after he had eaten grass all day, and drank water in a pail very well, yet he continued to bellow and scrape, and to stare very wildly. I took him in again, gave him the first medicine, and kept him close from much light till Tuesday night, then drove him to his fellows, he being perfect well, and so continued. When thou hast
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:206326:64"/>need, follow this example, with any beast what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever.</p>
                  <p>If there be any wounds with biting, you may heal them as other dogs bitings are healed; for this medicine is onely to preserve them from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mad. With this onely medicine I cured four men, and five women, since the year 1657, <hi>viz.</hi> two of the men, and one woman, after they had got what help they could, both by physick, Priests charms, and were cast into the sea, and yet were not cured, but began to be troubled in their minds, and could not sleep, yet had present help by this medicine. Also the man and the maid that were bitten with the mad wolf in <hi>Lemana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han,</hi> and dogs many, and some swine. But they are the worse to cure, if once they begin to be mad, there's no help, but kill them.</p>
                  <p>For small cattle give a little dose; as to a calf, a quarter of a pint; to a sheep, four or five spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls; to any kind of poultry, one spoonful. In the year 1652, I was called to see a heifer that was mad, at a friends house in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> where I then lived, but she was past cure. And they had a mad gander also, both bitten by a small house dog of their own, but I was called too late to have a cure of either.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Adder stinging to help, though not in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE adder is an eal-like serpent, not known in <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet many in <hi>England;</hi> and when a beast or horse is stung with one of them, the place will inflame, swell, and ranckle, and so pain the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:206326:65"/>beast, that he will soon dye thereof, if remedie be not found.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Signs of Adders stinging are;</head>
               <p>THE wounded member swells suddenly, is excessive hot, and the beast hath ragious pain, doth swell at the place, and is restless, and eats very little, and few are helped of this sorance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The remedy is,</head>
               <p>Take three or four pound of the tender buds of an ash tree, or the crops, or the green bark thereof, which ever you make use of, beat very small, and mix the ewith three pints of sallet oyl, and as much sack, or very strong ale; then strain it, and give it to the beast at six times in three days, morning and evening. Also take of the said ash tree buds or bark, beat it small with salt, and lay it to the venom'd place, or the great but roots beaten with salt, and laid to it, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:65"/>
            <head>An Alphabetical Table, of all the Disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and Sorances treated of in this Book, as followeth.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>ADder stinging, though not in <hi>Ireland, Page. 109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ague in Calves, or other cattle, <hi>Page. 1</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>Barbs in a beast's mouth, <hi>Page. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biting with a mad dog to cure, <hi>Page. 107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Blain on the tongue to help, <hi>Page. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Blood in beast's backs, <hi>Page. 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bones broken, or loose to knit, <hi>Page. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bulls their diseases cured, <hi>Page. 93</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>COugh in cattle cured, <hi>Page. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conoth worm nature cure, <hi>Page. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Closh, or founder in the feet, <hi>Page. 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collick in cattle cured, <hi>Page. 88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Crowling, or crying of the Guts, <hi>Page. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cut with a weapon, or hurt,</item>
               <item>Cud of a beast lost, <hi>Page. 65</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:66"/>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>DEw bolne in cattle cured, <hi>Page. 30</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>EYes, their diseases and hurts,</item>
               <item>Haw in the eye, discript. &amp; cure, <hi>Page. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Web in the eye cured, <hi>Page. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Stroke in the eye cured, <hi>Page. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>My own cure for all these, <hi>Page. 44</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>FEaver in cattle to help, <hi>Page. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Feaver pestilent to help, <hi>Page. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Flux of the belly remedied, <hi>Page. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Flux of blood to stay, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fluxes to stop, <hi>Page. 88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Flowing of the Gall to help, <hi>Page. 82</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>GArget in the throat cured, <hi>Page. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Garget on the tongue cured, <hi>Page. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Garget in the mawe, in beast's horns, or sheep, <hi>Page. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Garget of wind cured, <hi>Page. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Garget got by hurts remedied, <hi>Page. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Garget got by biting of a dog help'd</item>
               <item>Garget in sheep cured, <hi>Page. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Goaring of a beast remedied, <hi>Page. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Goaring in any out part, not the belly, <hi>Page. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:206326:66"/>
               <item>Gurling or rumbling in the belly, <hi>Page, 87</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>HIde-bound in a beast to help, <hi>Page, 83</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>IMposthums, often cured,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>KIne, diseases proper to them cured, <hi>Page, 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If a cow cannot calve to help her, <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If she cannot clean to help her, <hi>Page, 99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Falling out of the Matrix cured, <hi>Page, 100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>New calved sick with drinking <hi>Page, 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>White wast in a cow to help, <hi>Page, 103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ʋddern of a cow hurt or inflamed, <hi>Page, 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Milk wanting in a cow new calved, <hi>Page, 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Knees of cattle swoln to help, <hi>Page, 78</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>LIce on cattle to kill, <hi>Page, 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Loose teeth to fasten, <hi>Page, 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lungs grown, a bad disease to cure,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>MAd dog biting, often cured, <hi>Page, 107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mange on cattle cured, <hi>Page, 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Milting of a heast, <hi>Page, 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Murren amongst cattle to cure, <hi>Page, 8</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:67"/>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>PAntasie in a beast to cure, <hi>Page 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pallet of the mouth inflamed, <hi>Page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pallet faln to remedy, <hi>Page 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Piss, if cannot do it help, <hi>Page 83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pissing of blood helped, <hi>Page 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Purging things good for it, <hi>Page 87</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>QƲid of a beast lost to recover,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>ROt in cattle to help, <hi>Page 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rot with flouks in their livers; <hi>Page 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rot dry, or lung grown bad, <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Scabs or gauls on cattle to help, <hi>Page 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sineues to knit, <hi>Page 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Shrew-run to help, often proved <hi>Page 89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Springs, a swelling in the belly by blood, <hi>Page 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Swelling by eating a tine-worm, swelling by eating venomous herbs, or poysonous grass, <hi>Page 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spaven on the hough to cure, <hi>Page 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Staggers in cattle to cure, <hi>Page 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Signs to know a mad dog, <hi>Page 111</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:206326:67"/>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>TƲrn, or turning diseases, <hi>Page 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tetter on cattle to cure, <hi>Page 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Trenches to cure, <hi>Page 26</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>WArts on the feet of cattle cured, <hi>Page 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Want of digestion remedied, <hi>Page 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wood-evil, or cramp cured, <hi>Page 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Worm in the tayl to cure, <hi>Page 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Worms in cattle, or calves, <hi>Page 86</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>